<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="guide-standards.layout">
 <title>Layout of the Documentation</title>
 
 <para>
  The documentation might seem complex at first, but it is really very simple.
  This section will give you an idea of how the documentation is laid out, so
  you can easily work with it.
 </para>
 <para>
  <filename>manual.xml</filename> is the big cheese for all the documentation.
  It defines the chapters and is used by the XML parser to generate the docs.
  If you need to add a new chapter, this is the file to see.
 </para>
 <para>
  The biggest chunk of the documentation is stored in the <literal>sections/</literal>
  directory.  Unless it is a general file on the top level of the manual, files
  should be contained in sub-directories in the <literal>sections/</literal>
  directory.  For instance, Gallery 1.x files are located in the 
  <literal>gallery1/</literal> directory in the <literal>sections/</literal>
  directory.
 </para>
 <para>
  In each of the sub-directories of <literal>sections/</literal>, there will
  be an <filename>index.xml</filename> file, which defines the layout for
  the chapter.  Normally, this file just contains entity references to all
  the sections in the chapter (see below).  For example, the <filename>
  index.xml</filename> for the <literal>guide-standards/</literal> directory
  looks something like this:
  <screen>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
   
 &chapters.guide-standards.basics;
 &chapters.guide-standards.formatting; 
 &chapters.guide-standards.generating;
 &chapters.guide-standards.layout;
]]>
  </screen>
  Where these entities come from is described below.
 </para>
 <para>
  Most every file used in the documentation can be referenced by an entity (as
  shown above).  This allows us to easily include the documentation.  File
  entities are described in the <filename>files.ent</filename> file in the
  base directory of the docs module.  The file is commented and should be
  easy to understand.
 </para>
 <para>
  Other entities, such as notes that will appear in the documentation often,
  should appear in the <filename>global.ent</filename> file.  Entities should
  be defined here if they appear in multiple places in the documentation, so
  they can be updated in one place but automagically affect multiple places
  in the documentation.
 </para>
</sect1>
