<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery-remote.faq">
	<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

	<qandaset>

		<qandaentry id="gallery-remote.faq.1">
			<question>
				<para>
How do I upgrade Gallery Remote?
				</para>
			</question>
			<answer>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
Download the newest zip patch for Gallery Remote from <ulink url="http://jpmullan.com/galleryupdates/">the nightly site</ulink>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
Extract the zip file on top of your existing GR install (you need to have previously installed a full
version of Gallery Remote), and overwrite all files.
							<emphasis>Remember to stop GR before doing this!</emphasis>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
Restart Gallery Remote.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</answer>
		</qandaentry>

		<qandaentry id="gallery-remote.faq.2">
			<question>
				<para>
I found a bug, what do I do?
				</para>
			</question>
			<answer>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
<emphasis>Before you report bugs against Gallery Remote, please take some time to verify that what you
were trying to do in Gallery Remote can be performed using the web interface in Gallery.</emphasis>
						</para>
						<para>
A lot of the bugs reported against GR are actually installation problems that
affect Gallery even when Gallery Remote is not involved: upload permissions,
PHP settings, etc.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
With any bug report, you need to provide the following info:
						</para>
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
the version of the Gallery installation you were trying to interact with.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
the version of the Gallery Remote installation, as well as the VM and OS under
which Gallery Remote was being used.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
if the bug is that Gallery Remote doesn't do what's expected: it doesn't log you
on, images aren't uploaded right, you get wierd error messages, please also attach
the log or a portion thereof to the bug report.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</listitem>

				</orderedlist>
			</answer>
		</qandaentry>

		<qandaentry id="gallery-remote.faq.3">
			<question>
				<para>
Log, what log?
				</para>
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
If you encounter a problem, the logging system may be some help, and we will definitely request it
if you ask for support.  By default, GR writes most log information to the file <filename>GalleryRemoteLog.txt
</filename> in the temporary directory for your platform. If you want to see more detailed information
there, you can set the Log level to "Detailed, very verbose" in the Gallery Remote preferences dialog.
				</para>
				<para>
If you would like to see the log unfold as you use the application rather than having
it go to a file, you should change the following:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
In file <filename>GalleryRemote.properties</filename> (this is the preferences file, explained in the
<link linkend="gallery-remote.using.preferences">Preferences section</link>), set
								<screen>
toSysOut=true
								</screen>
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
In file <filename>Gallery Remote.lax</filename> (in the directory where Gallery Remote was installed),
set:
								<screen>
lax.stdout.redirect=console
								</screen>
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>
Caution: Be careful before posting your log to forums or sending it to anyone: your password is printed in clear text in several places.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</qandaentry>

		<qandaentry id="gallery-remote.faq.4">
			<question>
				<para>
Building thumbnails and displaying preview is slow (Linux, MacOS)
				</para>
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
Whereas on Windows, ImageMagick and jpegtran are installed by the installer, on other OSes,
they are not automatically installed, and must be installed by the end-user.
				</para>
				<para>
Please make sure that these products are available in your Unix <varname>PATH</varname> variable: you should be able to run them from a command-line as:
<literallayout><command>jpegtran</command>
<command>convert</command></literallayout>
				</para>
				<para>
If the commands above do not work, you should download and install these packages:
<ulink url="http://jpegclub.org/">http://jpegclub.org/</ulink> and
<ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org">http://www.imagemagick.org</ulink>.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</qandaentry>

		<qandaentry id="gallery-remote.faq.5">
			<question>
				<para>
Rotating pictures seems to work (the thumbnails are rotated), but the pictures are uploaded without being rotated
				</para>
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
Same as <link linkend="gallery-remote.faq.4">above</link>.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</qandaentry>

	</qandaset>

</sect1>
