<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery-remote.i18n">
	<title>Gallery Remote Internationalization and Localization</title>

	<sect2 id="gallery-remote.i18n.translators">
		<title>Instructions for translators</title>

		<para>
   First, thank you for considering helping the project by donating time and effort
   to translate Gallery Remote to a new language or improving an existing translation.
		</para>

  <para>
   The process for creating or updating Gallery Remote translations is significantly
   different from that of Gallery (1 and 2) translations. Please read this document carefully.
  </para>

  <sect3>
   <title>Setting up Gallery Remote for localization work</title>

   <sect4>
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>
     First, you need to install Gallery Remote. Grab a recent build from the
     <ulink url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=phpWiki&amp;file=index&amp;pagename=Gallery%20Remote">download page</ulink> and install it.
    </para>
    <para>
     Also install the latest <ulink url="http://jpmullan.com/galleryupdates/">beta patch</ulink> to make sure
     the language you intend to work on hasn't already been integrated. You can find help on how to do
     that in the <link linkend="gallery-remote.faq.1">FAQ</link> 
    </para>

   </sect4>

   <sect4>
    <title>Configuration</title>

    <para>
     You then need to change a few things to put Gallery Remote in a mode that will make it more comfortable
     to work on translation.
    </para>

    <para>
     Find the <link linkend="gallery-remote.using.preferences">preferences file</link> and add the following line:
     <screen>uiLocaleDev=true</screen>
    </para>

   </sect4>

   <sect4>
    <title>New language file</title>

    <para>
     Then go to the <filename>img</filename> folder in your Gallery Remote folder and create an empty file for your
     language, with the following naming convention:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
     <listitem><para>if the language you intend to work on is a competely new language, the
      filename will be <filename>GRResources_<replaceable>languagecode</replaceable>.properties</filename>
     </para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>if the language you intend to work on is a national modification of an existing base language, the
      filename will be <filename>GRResources_<replaceable>languagecode</replaceable>_<replaceable>countrycode</replaceable>.properties</filename>
     </para>
     <para>
      In this case you also need to extract the main language from <filename>GalleryRemote.jar</filename>
      (the Java SDK must be in your path) and you must have a console in the Gallery Remote
      installation folder):
      <command>
       jar xfv GalleryRemote.jar com/gallery/GalleryRemote/resources/GRResources.properties
      </command>
      and move it to the <filename>img</filename> folder.
     </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     You can find the standardized list of language codes <ulink url="http://ftp.ics.uci.edu/pub/ietf/http/related/iso639.txt">here</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
     You can find the standardized list of country codes <ulink url="http://userpage.chemie.fu-berlin.de/diverse/doc/ISO_3166.html">here</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
     Capitalization is important: language codes are lowercase, while country codes are uppercase.
    </para>

   </sect4>

   <sect4>
    <title>Selecting the new language in Gallery Remote</title>

    <para>
     Run Gallery Remote, go in the Preferences dialog. Your new language should be available
     in the Language selection. You need to restart Gallery Remote for the language to
     be used in the user interface.
    </para>
   </sect4>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
   <title>Installing and running the localization application: ResBundleEdit</title>

   <para>
    You can download RedBundleEdit from the <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=94241">Sourceforge project page</ulink>.
   </para>

   <para>
    To install it, just put the resulting file in a convenient place on your hard-drive, for example
    your Gallery Remote folder.
   </para>

   <para>
    If Java is installed on your machine, running ResBundleEdit is as simple as double-clicking on the JAR file.
    If that doesn't work, you can open a console or Command Window, set the current directory to the
    directory you put the JAR in and type <command>java -jar ResBundleEdit.jar</command>.
   </para>

   <para>
    When it's launched for the first time, ResBundleEdit show the properties files in the folder
    it was started from. You can change this in the Options dialog, and set the default directory
    to the <filename>img</filename> folder inside your Gallery Remote installation.
   </para>

   <para>
    You should then be able to double-click on <filename>GRResources.properties</filename> in the
    list of files on the left.
   </para>

   <para>
    The resource file will open in the right part of the window. There should be one column for
    resource keys, then one column for each language file in the folder. Your new language should be
    a column with nothing in it.
   </para>

   <para>
    The translation process is just a matter of translating every key and adding the translation to
    your language. Good luck...
   </para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
   <title>Translation guidelines</title>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>Start with an empty language file, do not copy the main language file.</para>
     <para>Gallery Remote will automatically default to the text in the main language (English) file if
     a given key is absent in your language file, and will signal this by
     appending *** before the English text.</para>
     <para>If you copy text from the English file to your file, you'll make it harder for
     yourself and the Gallery team to identify which strings have been translated and which have not.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Always use ResourceBundleEditor to edit a language file, do not use a standard
     text editor. Java requires a special encoding for language files.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>You can ask ResBundleEdit to close those locales that you don't need to work
     on to have more room for your locale and the default/main/English locale.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>If a string has text like:
     <screen>{0}</screen>
     <screen>{1, number, integer}</screen>
     do not translate the text inside the brackets, it will be replaced at runtime by
     the application.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Test your translation often by running Gallery Remote and making sure that your translation makes sense.
     You have to restart Gallery Remote for it to take new translations into account; translations
     are not loaded dynamically.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
   <title>Sending completed translations</title>

   <para>
    When your translation is complete, you can either add it to the
    <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?atid=582564&amp;group_id=7130">Gallery language tracker</ulink>
    (preferred), with a title like:
    <command>[GR] language file for <replaceable>language</replaceable></command>
    or send it to me via email (paour AT users DOT sourceforge DOT net).
   </para>
  </sect3>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="gallery-remote.i18n.users">
		<title>Using Gallery Remote with a non-roman Gallery</title>

		<para>
		</para>
	</sect2>

</sect1>
