<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery-remote.problems">
 <title>Known Problems</title>

	<sect2 id="gallery-remote.problems.bundled">
		<title>Bundled (or not) software</title>
		<para>Gallery Remote uses two external and native applications to manipulate images.
 			The reason for this is primarily that the loading large images in the Java VM
 			is not a good idea and so ImageMagick is used to create thumbnails, previews
 			and prepare images for uploading; all in a separate memory space.</para>
		<para>Anyway... this means that ImageMagick and jpegtran (both open-source
 			packages) need to be set up and Gallery Remote has to be configured to
 			use them. This depends on the platform you're running...</para>
        <para>Newer versions of ImageMagick can yield substancial improvements
            in the time it takes to load images into GR, often speeding that up by a factor
            of 2.</para>

        <sect3 id="gallery-remote.problems.bundled.win">
			<title>Windows</title>
			<para>The Windows installer for Gallery Remote includes both ImageMagick and
				jpegtran, so you shouldn't have to do anything to set them up.</para>
			<para>However, there have been reports of ImageMagick being broken
				in some installs. The most common is an error message that
				goes like this:
				<literal>This application has failed to start because MSVCR70.dll was not found. Reinstalling may fix this problem.</literal>.
				You can fix this by <ulink url="http://www.dll-files.com/dllindex/dll-files.shtml?msvcr70">downloading MSVCR70.dll</ulink>
				and copying it into your <filename>C:\windows\system32</filename>
 				(or <filename>C:\WINNT\system32</filename> on older NT-based systems).
				</para>
			<para>If that doesn't work, you should <ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org/">download the full version of
				ImageMagick</ulink> and install it. Gallery Remote (1.4.2-b24 and later) should automatically
                locate ImageMagick (if the reg.exe utility is available, which is the case on W2k anx XP).
                If it doesn't find it automatically, you need to edit the Gallery
				Remote configuration file <filename>imagemagick/im.properties</filename>
				(inside the Gallery Remote installation directory) and change the
				value of <varname>imConvertPath</varname> to point to the convert.exe
 				executable in the installation of ImageMagick.</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3 id="gallery-remote.problems.bundled.mac">
			<title>Mac OS X</title>
			<para>The Mac package includes jpegtran, but it does not include ImageMagick,
 				so you need to <ulink url="http://www.entropy.ch/software/macosx/#imagemagick">download ImageMagick from Apple</ulink> 
 				and install it.</para>
			<para>No other action should be necessary: the package is always installed
				in <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename>.</para>
			<para>If you have already installed ImageMagick using Fink, it is probably installed in
				<filename>/sw/bin</filename>. In that case, you can either create symlinks for
				<filename>/sw/bin/convert</filename> to <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename> or
				edit the file <filename>im.properties</filename> in <filename>Gallery Remote.app/Contents/Resource/Java/img.jar</filename>
				to change <varname>imConvertPath</varname> to the real path for the <filename>convert</filename> executable.
            </para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3 id="gallery-remote.problems.bundled.linux">
			<title>Linux</title>
			<para>The Linux package includes neither utility, but luckily, most
				Linux distributions include ImageMagick and/or jpegtran.</para>
			<para>If yours doesn't, the <ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org">ImageMagick site</ulink>
				has pre-built packages. RPMs and such of jpegtran can be found
				everywhere.
			</para>
			<para>If the packages are installed in your PATH, no further action should
				be necessary. If it doesn't work, you may want to edit the Gallery
				Remote configuration file <filename>imagemagick/im.properties</filename>
				and <filename>jpegtran/jpegtran.properties</filename>
				(inside the Gallery Remote installation directory) and change the
				value of <varname>imConvertPath</varname> (<varname>jpegtranPath</varname>)
 				to point to the respective executables.</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>

</sect1>
