<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery-remote.software">
 <title>Bundled Software</title>
 <para>
  The following software is bundled with Gallery Remote, to provide some of the functions provided.
  No particular action is necessary to install these packages. The following information is provided
  for the benefit of curious users and developers only.
 </para>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery-remote.software.imagemagick">
  <title>ImageMagick</title>
  <para>
   ImageMagick can be found <ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org/">here</ulink>.
   We use ImageMagick to resize images prior to uploading them.
   In the future, we'll implement features such as watermarking or arbitrary ImageMagick manipulation.
  </para>
  <para>
   <ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org/www/Copyright.html">ImageMagick</ulink> is licensed under its own license.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery-remote.software.jsx">
  <title>JSX</title>
  <para>
   JSX can be found <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/directory/devel/conversion/JavaSerialization.html">here</ulink>.
   We use JSX to provide save/load support. In the future, this may be used to allow external tools to 
   automatically generate projects that can then be loaded into Gallery Remote.
  </para>
  <para>
   JSX is licensed under the GPL.
  </para>
  <para>
   Since we started including JSX into our build, the free and open version of JSX has
   vanished from the above URL, to be replaced by a new, but neither free nor open
   version (JSX 2). Despite this, the license for JSX 1.0.7.4, which Gallery uses, remains
   valid, although the corresponding package is no longer available.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="gallery-remote.software.jpegtran">
  <title>Jpegtran</title>
  <para>
   The Win32 version of Jpegtran, compiled and patched by <ulink url="http://sylvana.net/jpegcrop/">Guido Vollbeding</ulink>.
   We use Jpegtran to rotate JPEG pictures before upload. In the future, it may also be used to crop pictures.
  </para>
  <para>
   Jpegtran doesn't appear to have any particular license, but is obviously redistributable, 
   since it comes with most Linux distributions. Guido's version is freely downloadable.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="gallery-remote.software.jarbundler">
  <title>Jar Bundler Ant Task</title>
  <para>
   The Mac executable is made with the Jar Bundler Ant task, which is made available by Seth Morabito.
   The Ant task is available <ulink url="http://www.loomcom.com/jarbundler/index.html">here</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The Jar Bundler Ant Task is licensed under the GPL.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="gallery-remote.software.metadata">
  <title>MetadataExtractor</title>
  <para>
   Gallery Remote uses the MetadataExtractor library, by Drew Noakes, to read the EXIF Orientation
   tags, in order to figure out whether it should automatically rotate the images.
   The library is available <ulink url="http://drewnoakes.com/code/exif/index.html">here</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
   MetadataExtractor has been placed in the public domain by its author.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
