<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-admin.backup">
 <title>Backup and Restore</title>
 
 <para>
  There are three ways to backup your Gallery.  They are both described here.
 </para>
 
 <warning>
  <para>
   There are some caveats to backing up your albums!  Please read the 
   <link linkend="gallery1-admin.backup.caveats">caveats section</link>
   for more information.
  </para>
 </warning>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.backup.tar">
  <title>Using <command>tar</command></title>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-admin.backup.tar.backup">
   <title>Backup</title>
   
   <para>
    Backup using <command>tar</command> is relatively simple, but you must have
    shell access.  Run the following command in the parent directory of your
    albums directory:
    <screen>
     tar -czvf albums.tar.gz albums
    </screen>
    This will give you a file, <filename>albums.tar.gz</filename> which contains
    your albums directory.
   </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-admin.backup.tar.restore">
   <title>Restore</title>
   
   <para>
    Restoring the albums directory using <command>tar</command> is also easy.
    Run this command in the parent directory of your albums directory (or where
    you want your albums directory to be)
    <screen>
     tar -xvzf albums.tar.gz
     chmod -R 777 albums
    </screen>
    The second command is as important as the first!
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.backup.ftp">
  <title>Using FTP</title>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-admin.backup.ftp.backup">
   <title>Backup</title>
   
   <para>
    Basically, to backup your albums using FTP, just download the whole albums
    directory.  This will give you an exact copy of the directory on your
    local computer, which you can hold on to in case it's needed
   </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-admin.backup.ftp.restore">
   <title>Restore</title>
   
   <para>
    To restore your albums directory using FTP, just re-upload the albums directory
    that you downloaded to your computer.  The only problem is that the new
    files <emphasis>MUST BE CHMODDED 0777 RECURSIVELY</emphasis>.  Recursively
    means <emphasis>every file and every directory</emphasis>.  This can be a
    pain using FTP, but is necessary or you will recieve errors.
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.backup.script">
  <title>Using the backup script (1.3.4 and above)</title>
  
  <para>
   Gallery 1.3.4 is equipped with a new <filename>backup_albums.php</filename>
   script to backup your albums.  It's located in your <filename>setup/</filename>
   directory.  To use it, you must copy it out of the <filename>setup/</filename>
   directory and put it in your base gallery directory.
  </para>
  <para>
   Then navigate to it using your browser, when logged in as an admin.  For example,
   <filename>http://www.example.com/gallery/backup_albums.php</filename>.  From
   there you will have a number of options. 
   <warning>
    <para>
     Using the "All Files" option will more than likely give a HUGE file, and may
     take a while.  We recommend just backing up the data files.
    </para>
   </warning>
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    WINDOWS USERS -- It is recommended that you just use WinZip or
    <link linkend="gallery1-admin.backup.ftp">FTP</link> to backup your files
    because most Windows servers don't have any of the utilities that the
    backup script needs.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.backup.caveats">
  <title>Caveats</title>
  
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     When backing up on one platform and trying to restore on another platform,
     i.e. transmogrify from Windows to UNIX, you will need to eliminate all
     occuring "\r" (LF) in all the .dat files. Double-Breaks like "\r\n" will
     have to change to "\n".  Utilities like <command>dos2unix</command> and
     can help in this realm.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect2>
    
</sect1>
