<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-admin.basics">
 <title>Basics</title>
 
 <para>
  This section should give you basic information about Gallery and how to
  manage it.
 </para>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.basics.login">
  <title>Logging In</title>
  
  <para>
   When you ran the <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">configuration
   wizard</link>, you specified an admin password.  Now it's time to use it!
   On the main Gallery page, click "[login]"  Using the username <literal>admin
   </literal> and the password you specified during configuration, login to 
   Gallery!  You now have full admin priviliges
  </para>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.basics.creating-albums">
  <title>Creating Albums</title>
  
  <para>
   Creating albums is extremely simple, just click "[new album]".  The new album
   is created.  You should see the message "Hey! Add some photos"  However, before
   adding photos, it's usually a good idea to modify some of the album properties,
   such as title, description, and name.
  </para>
  <para>
   Go back to the main Gallery page by clicking the link in the top right by the
   up arrow.  You should see the new album on the main page.  To edit the title
   of the new album, click "[edit title]" by the current title (for new albums, it
   defaults to "Untitled").  To edit the description, do the same thing by clicking
   on "[edit description]".  Finally, rename the album.  Click on the link in the
   sentence "Hey! Rename this album so that the URL is not so generic".  Once you've
   done this, you're ready to add photos.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.basics.adding-photos">
  <title>Adding Photos</title>
  
  <para>
   To add photos in an album, navigate to the album and click "[add photos]".  You
   can now browse your computer and upload photos, adding an optional caption with each
   image.  You can also change the number of file upload boxes displayed by using
   the select box.  Another option is to upload files to your server and then specify
   the path on the server (<emphasis>the directory must be readable by the webserver user
   </emphasis>).  Finally, you can specify a URL (e.g. http://www.example.com) to "leech"
   images from.  Note that you cannot specify the direct URL of the image, only a page
   to a webpage that contains images.  Click "Upload Now" or "Submit URL or directory"
   and you're on your way.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.basics.editing-item-properties">
  <title>Editing Item Properties</title>
  
  <para>
   Each item (photo or movie) in Gallery has a list of properties that can
   be edited.
  </para>
  <sect3 id="gallery1-admin.basics.editing-item-properties.images">
   <title>Image Properties</title>
   
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Edit Text -- Edits caption, description, keywords, and other custom
      fields defined for the image
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Edit Thumbnail -- Uses a java applet to edit which part of the image
      should be shown as the thumbnail
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Rotate/Flip Photo -- Self-explanatory, rotates or flips the photo. Rotate
      can be done in 90 degree increments.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Highlight Photo -- Use this photo to represent the album
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Move Photo -- Move the photo or group of photos (i.e. position in an
      album or to another album)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Hide Photo -- Hides a photo.  Only admins and the album owner can see
      hidden photos.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Delete Photo -- Deletes the photo (no undo)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Change Owner -- Changes the owner of the photo (item ownership added in
      Gallery 1.4.0)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-admin.basics.editing-item-properties.movies">
   <title>Movie Properties</title>
   
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Edit Text -- Edits caption, description, keywords, and other custom
      fields defined for the movie
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Move Movie -- Move the movie or a group of items (i.e. position in the
      album or to another album)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Hide Movie -- Hides the movie.  Only admins and the album owner can see
      hidden movies.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Delete Movie -- Deletes the movie (no undo)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Change Owner -- Changes the owner of the movie (item ownership added in
      Gallery 1.4.0)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.basics.editing-album-properties">
  <title>Edit Album Properties</title>
  
  <para>
   When you are an admin or album owner, you can edit certain properties about
   an album.  When you are an in album, there will be a number of links in the
   top right of the screen.  Each is explained below.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Add Photos -- Add photos to the album (see the
     <link linkend="gallery1-admin.basics.adding-photos">adding photos section</link>
     for more information)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Add Photo -- Add a single photo, but you can specify all the custom fields during
     upload
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Rename Album -- Change the name of the album (i.e. the name in the URL)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     New Nested Album -- Create a sub-album in this album
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Custom Fields -- Edit the custom fields defined for this album.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Captions -- Edit captions for the images in the album (more efficent that
     editing each item's caption individually)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Sort -- Sort the images by various critiera
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Resize all -- Resize all the photos in the album to a certain size
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Rebuild thumbs -- Rebuild all the thumbnails in the album
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Permissions -- Edit the permissions for the album (see the
     <link linkend="gallery1-admin.users">users administration guide</link>
     for more information)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem> 
    <para>
     Properties -- Edit various properties of the album, including title, summary,
     and various properties related to the album's appearance
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     View All Comments -- View all user comments in the album (only seen if commenting
     is enabled)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Slideshow -- (seen by all users) Display a slideshow of all the images in the
     album
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Logout -- Log out of Gallery
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect2>

</sect1>
