<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-admin.embedding">
 <title>Embedding Gallery</title>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.embedding.nuke">
  <title>PHP Nuke / PostNuke</title>
  
  <para>
   Embedding Gallery into PHP Nuke or PostNuke is incredibly easy.  We already
   assume you have successfully setup your CMS (Content Management System).
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Download Gallery, from the
     <ulink url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=phpWiki&amp;file=index&amp;pagename=Download">Download Page</ulink>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Untar Gallery and upload it to your Nuke <filename>modules/</filename> directory.
     It is very important that it goes in this directory
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Install Gallery just as if you were doing a non-nuke installation, see one
     of the following guides:
     <link linkend="gallery1-install.unix-shell">Unix with Shell Access</link>,
     <link linkend="gallery1-install.unix-ftp">Unix with FTP Access</link>,
     <link linkend="gallery1-install.windows">Windows on Apache</link>,
     <link linkend="gallery1-install.windows-iis">Windows on IIS</link>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Through Nuke, login as an admin and navigate to the "Modules" administration
     tool.  Install and activate Gallery (in Postnuke, you may need to "regenerate"
     the list of modules).  <emphasis>You must activate the module or only admins
     will be able to access it</emphasis>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Your Gallery is installed through Nuke!  In PHP-Nuke, Gallery should show
     up in the Modules block.  In PostNuke, you may need to manually add it to the
     menu.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <note>
   <simpara>
    Please consult the documentation in the /gallery/contrib directory for more
    information.  Embedding often requires some additional changes in the manner of
    file patches before it will work properly.
   </simpara>
  </note>
 
  <note>
   <simpara>
    You can change the name of the <filename>gallery</filename> directory in your
    <filename>modules/</filename> directory.  Gallery will detect the changes
    and do the right thing.
   </simpara>
  </note>
     
 </sect2>
 <sect2 id="gallery1-admin.embedding.mambo">
  <title>Mambo</title>
  
  <para>
   Gallery is in fact a Mambo component right out of the box! If you have an existing Mambo version 4.5 or newer
   installation, you'll have Gallery up and running embedded in your
   Mambo site in a jiffy. Gallery will even integrate seamlessly with
   your existing Mambo user information.
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     First, grab the latest version of Gallery from the <ulink
     url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=phpWiki&amp;file=index&amp;pagename=Download">Download
     Page</ulink>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Install Gallery just as if you were doing a non-Mambo
     installation, all on its own. See one of the following guides for
     further help here:
     <link linkend="gallery1-install.unix-shell">Unix with Shell Access</link>,
     <link linkend="gallery1-install.unix-ftp">Unix with FTP Access</link>,
     <link linkend="gallery1-install.windows">Windows on Apache</link>,
     <link linkend="gallery1-install.windows-iis">Windows on IIS</link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Make sure you have completed the Gallery setup all the way
     through. Don't worry too much about the look and feel out of the
     box just yet, because it will look slightly different once embedded into
     Mambo.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Now log into your Mambo administrator console and install Gallery as
     a component. The easiest method is to select <varname>Install/Uninstall</varname>
     from the <varname>Components</varname> menu.
	 <mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/gallery1-admin/component_menu.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
       <para>
	    The <varname>Components</varname> Menu in the Mambo administrator console
       </para>
      </caption>
     </mediaobject>
	 Since you already have Gallery
     installed (you did step 1, right?!), you'll want to choose "Install
     from directory". For "Install directory", enter the full
     path on disk to your <filename>gallery/contrib/mambo</filename>
     directory. It might look something like
     <filename>/home/www/mysite.com/htdocs/gallery/contrib/mambo</filename>. The
     Gallery setup Step 2 "Locations and URLs" tab has some full paths
     specified which might help here. Then click the <varname>Install</varname>
     button.
	 <mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/gallery1-admin/install_from_directory.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
       <para>
	    Specify the full path to your <filename>gallery/contrib/mambo</filename> directory
       </para>
      </caption>
     </mediaobject>
	 If it was successful, click <varname>Continue</varname>. Otherwise, it's
     likely you didn't enter the correct install path, so go back and
     double check it.
	 <mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/gallery1-admin/install_success.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
       <para>
        If you see this, you've added Gallery successfully
       </para>
      </caption>
     </mediaobject>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
	 Now, you should be able to select "Gallery" from the <varname>Components</varname> menu.
     You should then be at the Gallery component configuration page
     inside the Mambo admin page. There are three Mambo-specific
     settings for Gallery.
	 <mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/gallery1-admin/gallery_setup.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
       <para>
	    The Gallery component setup page
       </para>
      </caption>
     </mediaobject>
	 The path to Gallery is the same path as you
     entered earlier, only without the
     <filename>/contrib/mambo</filename> part at the end. This tells
     Mambo where to find your actual installation. The "Admin Level"
     sets the lowest-privilege user level allowed to have admin access
     to Gallery. Admin access allows the user to view, create, or
     delete any or all items in Gallery. In Mambo terminology,
     "Backend" users have a higher privilege level than "Frontend"
     users. The final setting on this page asks whether you'd like
     Gallery to suppress the right-hand module bar. This gives Gallery
     a little extra space in the browser window. Remember... you can
     return to this configuration page at any time to make changes
     later on. All other Gallery configuration can be done via the
     Gallery setup page you saw earlier.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You'll probably want to add Gallery to your main menu. From the
     Mambo admin page, go to the <varname>Menu</varname> menu and select "Menu
     Manager". For this example, we'll add Gallery to the main
     menu. Click the configuration button for the main menu Menu
     Items. You'll be presented with the existing menu contents. Click
     <varname>New</varname> from the top toolbar. Gallery is a Mambo Component, so
     select that. Give your menu item a display name and select
     Gallery from the component list. Set the rest of the options as
     you see fit and click Save from the toolbar. If all went well,
     you'll now have a link to your Gallery in your main menu from
     your Mambo page. If you're logged in as the administrator, click
     <varname>[new album]</varname> and get Gallerying!
	 <mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/gallery1-admin/main_menu.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
       <para>
	    Link to your embedded Gallery in the main menu
       </para>
      </caption>
     </mediaobject>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   If you get stuck at any point, remember that there's always help
   available on the Gallery website and in the forums.
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
