<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-admin.performance">
 <title>Performance Tips</title>
 
 <para>
  Gallery performance is very good for small to medium installations.  Because
  of Gallery's architecture, larger numbers of photos and albums can cause
  certain operations (like viewing the main page) to run slowly.  The sizes that
  trigger slowdowns vary greatly from depending on the capabilities of your
  server, but it's reasonable to say that over 5,000 photos will begin to
  get slow on a PIII 800Mhz machine, over 10,000 on a P4 2Ghz machine.  There
  are several things you can do to recover performance in these situations.
 </para>
 
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">Disable "Show Album Tree"</emphasis>.
    Removing this option allows Gallery to generate the index page without
    having to iterate through many different subalbums, requiring much time.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">Disable "Accurate Photo Count"</emphasis>
    (Introduced in 1.4.4-pl2).  Disabling this extremely slow method of counting 
    the number of albums and photos on the main page allows Gallery to generate
    the index page without recursing through all your albums.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">Keep albums small</emphasis>.  Try to avoid having
    albums that are huge -- split them further down into subalbums if possible.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">Cache the main page</emphasis>.  This is more involved
    than the other steps, and requires access to cron.  <emphasis>This method
    will give you the most performance increase</emphasis>.  It's also worth
    noting that if you using caching, the other features that we recommend
    you disable above don't affect the performance anymore, since the whole
    page is cached.
   </para>
   <para>
    Gallery, if it finds a certain cache file in its base directory
    (<filename>cache.html</filename>), will return the contents of that file
    (if it's up to date) instead of regenerating the whole main page
    for every user.  To reap the benefits of the cache, add this line to your
    crontab (<literal>crontab -e</literal> from the command line)
    <screen>
     */15 * * * * wget -O /path/to/your/gallery/cache.html http://www.example.com/gallery?gallery_nocache=yes
    </screen>
   </para>
   <para>
    This does mean that any updates that affect the main page will take up to 15
    minutes to appear for non-logged-in users, but it's a huge perforance
    enhancement.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 
</sect1>
