<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-install.config-wizard">
 <title>The Configuration Wizard</title>
 
 <para>
  The Gallery configuration wizard guides you through the steps of installing
  Gallery.  It will notify you of potential errors and help you setup Gallery.
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     RUN THE CONFIGURATION WIZARD by typing
     <blockquote>
      <para>
       http://www.example.com/gallery/setup/index.php
      </para>
     </blockquote>
     in your browser window. You will see a page that starts with this:
     <blockquote>
      <para>
       Gallery Setup: Step 1
      </para>
      <para>
       This is the Gallery system check page. This page will validate
       your installation to make sure that you have all the necessary
       components and permissions on this system and that everything is
       configured reasonably.
      </para>
      <para>
       Having problems? Try the Gallery Diagnostics Page and the Gallery
       Help Page.
      </para>
     </blockquote>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/diagnostics.gif" format="GIF" />
      </imageobject>  
      <caption>  
       <para>  
        Screenshot of the Gallery Diagnostics Page
       </para>
      </caption>
     </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
     Use the Diagnostics Page to help find out more about the PHP
     installation on your webserver, if you have NetPBM or ImageMagick
     located and configured correctly and to check your PHP session
     configuration.
    </para>
    <para>
     The other link takes you to the <ulink
     url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php&#63;op=modload&amp;name=phpWiki&amp;file=index&amp;pagename=Help">Gallery
     Help Page</ulink> at <ulink
     url="http://gallery.menalto.com/">gallery.menalto.com</ulink>&#8212;where
     you can find more detailed answers for any problems you might
     incur during installation.
    </para>
    <para>
     This first part will run through a series of automatic checks to
     see if you have a current version of PHP running, whether or not
     <function>Safe Mode</function> is off (you want it OFF), whether
     it can read your <filename>.htaccess</filename> file, if magic
     quotes are on or off, if <function>mod_rewrite</function> is
     installed, whether it can find NetPBM or ImageMagick binaries and
     to see if you have Jhead installed. There is also some information
     there about NetPBM and ImageMagick and links to more
     information.
    </para>
    <para>
     For all of the above you will either see a green text message that
     says: "SUCCESS", with a short list of what was found, or a yellow
     "WARNING!" message with a brief description of the problem.
    </para>
    <para>
     If the errors are minor (unable to locate paths automatically),
     you will see this message: "Your installation has warnings, but
     life is short so let's GO!" and a button to click to continue with
     the configuration of Gallery.
    </para>
    <para>
     Now you're on to the fun stuff! Step Two of the Gallery setup is
     where you enter the name you'd like to have appear for your
     Gallery, your admin password and the paths Gallery needs to know
     for where your albums will be stored, etc.
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/step2setup.gif" format="GIF" />
      </imageobject>  
      <caption>  
       <para>  
        Screenshot of Configuration Wizard, Step 2
      </para>
     </caption>
    </mediaobject>
   </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis>REMEMBER THE PASSWORD YOU ENTER. YOU WILL NEED IT LATER
    TO ADMINISTRATE YOUR GALLERY ONLINE.</emphasis> The default
    username is "admin" (without quotes).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Once you've successfully run the Configuration wizard, Gallery
    will ask you to secure certain files before you can enter the
    Gallery. These are the same 3 files you applied permissions to
    above. This time you apply the permissions as follows:
    <programlisting>
     chmod 644 .htaccess
     chmod 644 config.php
     chmod 400 setup
    </programlisting>
    These directions are for Unix/Linux installs only.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you're on Windows, you cannot chmod files.  Instead, run the 
    <filename>secure.bat</filename> file, located in your gallery directory.
    This will tighten up security, and disallow the usage of the
    configuration wizard. If you want to redo any configuration tasks, run
    <filename>configure.bat</filename> from the same directory, do your 
    changes and run <filename>secure.bat</filename> again.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
</sect1>
