<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<!--
NOTE TO CONTRIBUTORS: THIS FAQ SHOULD BE CONSTANTLY UPDATED.  PLEASE
ADD OR EDIT WHATEVER YOU WANT, AS LONG AS IT'S NOT A DRASTIC CHANGE
-->

<sect1 id="gallery1-install.faq">
 <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

 <warning>
  <para>
   These FAQ items are a totally re-vamped version from the old FAQ.  The
   numbers are <emphasis>not the same</emphasis>.  If you came here from a
   forum post, please keep in mind that the FAQ has been changed.
  </para>
 </warning>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.faq.a" ischunk="yes">
  <title>A. Getting Gallery</title>
  
  <qandaset>
  
   <qandadiv label="A">

    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.a.1">
     <question>
      <para>
       How can I get the latest version of Gallery?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       There are two different 'latest' versions of Gallery. There is the version
       that has been released by the Gallery developers in a packaged format on
       the downloads page, and there is the source code which is available from
       CVS on SourceForge. Since developers are continuously adding new features
       and tweaking the codebase, the Gallery packages will tend to be more stable
       than the version you'll get from CVS. However, the version in CVS will have
       more current bugfixes and neat modifications. The version in CVS is
       typically pretty stable, since the developers use it to power their own
       personal Galleries, but it is bound to have the occasional major glitch.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.a.2">
     <question>
      <para>
       How can I get the latest CVS version of Gallery?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       The CVS binaries are a prerequisite. You can get them from cvshome.org.
       To download the initial copy of the source run these commands:
       <screen>
        % cvs -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.Gallery.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/gallery login
       </screen>
       When it asks for a password just hit enter.
       <screen>
        % cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.Gallery.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/gallery co gallery
       </screen>
       Once you have a version of Gallery that you've downloaded via CVS all you
       have to do is:
       <screen>
        % sh configure.sh; cvs -z3 update -APd
       </screen>
       <emphasis>
        Don't forget to put Gallery in config mode before doing the update or your
        setup directory won't get updated!
       </emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
       CVS nightlies can also be downloaded from <ulink url="http://jpmullan.com/galleryupdates/">
       http://jpmullan.com/galleryupdates/</ulink>.
      </para>	
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
   
   </qandadiv>
       
  </qandaset>
       
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.faq.b" ischunk="yes">
  <title>B. Configuring Gallery</title>
 
  <qandaset>
  
   <qandadiv label="B">
  
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.b.1">
     <question>
      <para>
       The setup page tells me that mod_rewrite is not installed. Since mod_rewrite is
       optional, how do I configure this option?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Mod_rewrite is a module that is compiled with Apache.  To enable it, you
       must have root access to the server.  Unless you compiled Apache by
       yourself, most distributions will include mod_rewrite, but not necessarily
       enabled it.  The most common way to do so is this:
       <screen>
        LoadModule rewrite_module libexec/mod_rewrite.so
        AddModule mod_rewrite.c
       </screen>
       For more information on mod_rewrite check out the
       <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/mod/mod_rewrite.html">Apache
       module mod_rewrite</ulink> page.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.b.2">
     <question>
      <para>
       Does Gallery work under Windows?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Many people have gotten Gallery to work under Windows using Apache.  However,
       Gallery does not interact well with IIS, because PHP still has some issues
       with executing programs like NetPBM and ImageMagick.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.b.3">
     <question>
      <para>
       How do I run PHP as a CGI?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Running PHP as a CGI is usually done when PHP is not available on your
       server (but you can execute cgi-bin scripts) or when the normal PHP
       installation is running in safe mode.  Note that in order for this to
       work, your server must be configured to read &htaccess; files, which your
       host can disable!
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Obtain a CGI version of PHP for your platform. You can downloads PHP
         binaries for various platforms on the
         <ulink url="https://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=7130&amp;release_id=167649">
         Gallery SourceForge Download Page</ulink>.  If you can't find a binary
         for your platform, but you have access to compile programs, you
         can configure PHP with this <command>configure</command> line.
         <screen>
          ./configure --enable-force-cgi-redirect --disable-safe-mode
          --with-config-file-path=/usr/local/lib/php-cgi
         </screen>
         Then run <command>make</command>.  The resulting binary will be called
         <command>php</command> in the <filename>sapi/cgi/</filename> directory
         of the PHP source.  Please submit the binary to
         <ulink url="mailto:joyoflinux@yahoo.com">Andrew Lindeman</ulink>, so
         he can include it on the download page.  Please only submit binaries
         that use that exact <command>configure</command> line, for consistancy
         reasons.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Upload the CGI version of PHP to the <filename>cgi-bin</filename>
         directory and call it <filename>php.cgi</filename>.  Upload it in
         BINARY FTP mode.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Chmod <filename>php.cgi</filename> 755 (<command>chmod 755 php.cgi</command>)
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Create a new directory in your webserver root called <filename>php-cgi
         </filename>
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Create a new &htaccess; file in your <filename>php-cgi</filename> directory
         and put the following lines in it:
         <screen>
          RemoveHandler .php
          AddType application/cgi-php php
          Action application/cgi-php /cgi-bin/php.cgi
         </screen>
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
       That should be it!  Install Gallery in your <filename>php-cgi</filename>
       directory.  <emphasis>It is extremely difficult to provide support for
       this, because there are many things that can go wrong and it's hard to
       diagnose the problem.</emphasis>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.b.4">
     <question>
      <para>
       How do I force .php files to use PHP4?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       In the rare case that your ISP has PHP3 and PHP4 installed on the same server,
       sometimes .php files will end up being parsed by the PHP3 parser, which Gallery
       can't run under.  To force .php files to use the PHP4 parser, add these to your
       &htaccess; file.
       <screen>
        &lt;Files *.php&gt;
         ForceType application/x-httpd-php
        &lt;/Files&gt;
       </screen>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.b.5">
     <question>
      <para>
       Where can I find the <command>unzip</command> and <command>zipinfo</command>
       binaries?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       You can download the latest unzip binary from the 
       <ulink url="http://www.info-zip.org/pub/infozip/UnZip.html">Info-Zip website
       </ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
       The recent releases of unzip no longer come with a zipinfo binary. That's
       ok, though because it's really just the same binary as unzip with a
       different name. Just make a copy of unzip and call it zipinfo and then
       tell Gallery about that on page 2 of the config wizard and you'll be all
       set.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>  

   </qandadiv>
 
  </qandaset>
 
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.faq.c" ischunk="yes">
  <title>C. Troubleshooting Gallery</title>
  
  <qandaset> 

   <qandadiv label="C">
  
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.1">
     <question>
      <para>
       When I try to access the configuration wizard, I get a <literal>500
       Internal Server Error</literal>.  What's up?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This is because your webserver doesn't allow you to use certain
       &htaccess; overrides.  The Gallery setup script tries to set some
       PHP settings, but this requires you to set <literal>AllowOverride Options
       FileInfo</literal> or disable the overrides.  If you have access to your
       <filename>httpd.conf</filename> file, add this to it:
       <screen>
        &lt;Directory "<filename>/path/to/your/gallery/directory</filename>"&gt;
         AllowOverride Options FileInfo
        &lt;/Directory&gt;
       </screen>
      </para>
      <para>
       If you don't have access to your <filename>httpd.conf</filename>, delete
       the &htaccess; file in the <filename>setup/</filename>
       directory.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.2">
     <question>
      <para>
       I've installed Gallery and all seems well. But when I try to upload an
       image it says <literal>Unable to make thumbnail(0)</literal> or 
       <literal>Invalid image</literal>. What gives?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This is a very common problem.  It's usually because the image manipulation
       program isn't getting called correctly, and this can happen for a number
       of reasons.  To diagnose the problem, follow these steps:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <emphasis>
          Verify that the binaries (NetPBM or ImageMagick) are installed
          correctly and are chmodded 0755 (including the directory they are in).
         </emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>
         One common installation mistake is to put the executable in a path
         that contains spaces. This happens often on Windows, if either
         package is installed in <filename>Program Files</filename>. The
         executables <emphasis>must not be installed in a path that contains spaces</emphasis>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Put Gallery back into configuration mode (see the tutorials earlier
         in the manual for details)
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem> 
        <para>
         Re-run the <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">configuration
         wizard</link>.  On step 2, select the option to put Gallery into
         <emphasis>debug mode</emphasis>.  Finish the configuration wizard and
         secure Gallery (this is described in the configuration wizard tutorial).
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Attempt to upload a picture using the web form interface, not the applet.
         There will be a whole lot more debugging messages now, and it will help
         to diagnose the problem.  Possible issues are listed below:
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
       If you see any of the following messages, the solutions are listed below
      </para>   
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <emphasis>Error in loading shared libraries</emphasis> -- Indicates
         that your dynamic library loader can't find a library that it needs.
         On Linux you can add the directory containing the appropriate library
         to <filename>/etc/ld.so.conf</filename> and then run <command>ldconfig
         -v</command> as root to fix this.  If you don't have root access to the
         server, either contact your host for help or download a new version
         of ImageMagick or NetPBM and use the new install instead.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <emphasis>Abort trap</emphasis> or <emphasis>Segmentation Fault</emphasis> or
         <emphasis>Cannot execute binary file</emphasis>
         -- probably means you installed the wrong binaries for your system (e.g.
         installed the FreeBSD binaries on a Linux system) or you uploaded the binaries
         in <literal>ASCII FTP mode</literal> instead of <literal>BINARY FTP mode</literal>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem> 
        <para>
         <emphasis>Permission Denied</emphasis> -- More than likely, your NetPBM directory
         or the actual NetPBM binaries are not chmodded 0755.  It could also mean that your
         host has disallowed you from executing programs; if this is the case, you must talk
         to them in order to get it resolved.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <emphasis>/usr/bin/convert: Not a JPEG file: starts with 0x0a 0x4d
         (/home/uspalmer/public_html/gallery/AUTHORS).</emphasis> -- This is a bug
         that has been fixed with the latest version of Gallery, please upgrade.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <emphasis>/usr/local/bin/convert: no delegate for this image format
         (/home/sites/home/web/albums/album_01/IMGP0215.jpg)</emphasis> -- This
         means ImageMagick doesn't have the appropriate libraries to handle
         a type of image format (in this case JPEG).  If you have root access, make
         sure the appropriate image libraries are installed or ask your host to
         verify this.  If not, you can try using NetPBM from the Gallery Download
         Page, which has all major image formats already included.  If you are using
         FreeBSD and installed ImageMagick from the ports collection, see
         <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.30">FAQ C.30</link>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <emphasis>Status: (expected 0)</emphasis> -- This means that Gallery is unable to 
         get a status message from PHP, which it relies on. One possible solution is that 
         your host has disabled some needed php functions. To determine if they have create
         a PHP file containing
          <screen>
<![CDATA[
<?php
echo ini_get("disable_functions");
?>
]]>
          </screen>
         If the output displays exec() see <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.29">FAQ C.29</link>.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
       If you still can't find a solution, try asking in the <ulink url="http://gallery.sf.net/forums.php">
       Gallery Support Forums</ulink>.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.3">
     <question>
      <para>
       My ISP has a really old version of PHP, something before 4.0.4pl1, which
       Gallery can't work with.  What do I do?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       First, send them a quick email and ask them if they are willing to upgrade.
       They should considering a PHP version this old is years and years old, and
       probably contains security problems.  Your only other good option is to
       install PHP as a CGI, as in <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.b.3">FAQ B.3
       </link>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.4">
     <question>
      <para>
       Whenever I try to upload grayscale JPEG images I get a <literal>Unable to
       make thumbnail</literal> error.  Why?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This is a bug in some versions of NetPBM that cause it to choke on grayscale
       images.  This is fixed in the version of NetPBM available on the Gallery
       download page.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.5">
     <question>
      <para>
       Whenever I try to upload an image in Gallery, I get all these errors about
       <literal>safe mode</literal>.  How can I fix this?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This is an unfortunate situation, because Gallery cannot run in safe mode.
       You have three options, listed below (try them in that order).
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Email your host asking them to turn off safe mode.  They are providing a
         service to you, and safe mode puts severe limits on that.  If they are a
         good host, they should listen
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Try <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.b.3">FAQ B.3</link>, where you can
         use PHP as a CGI.  This is usually pretty difficult, if you don't know exactly
         what you're doing.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Find another host that doesn't use safe mode.  Some are listed in the
         <ulink url="http://gallery.sourceforge.net/wiki.php?page=Web%20Hosting%20Referral%20Page">
         Gallery Hosting Referrals Page</ulink>
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.6">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why can't I upload big files (over a megabyte or two)?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Craig Goranson wrote a very informative <ulink url="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gallery-users&amp;m=102589601604892&amp;w=2">
       email</ulink> about how to fix this.
      </para>
      <note>
       <para>
        Gallery tries to override the <literal>upload_max_filesize</literal>
        and <literal>post_max_size</literal> directives in its &htaccess; file.
        This means that changing the setting globally may still result in it
        being overridden at the .htaccess level, so you may want to just change
        the directive there instead of globally.  Gallery tries to set both
        of the directives to about 20 megabytes, so this will only affect you
        if you're going to upload files over that size.
       </para>
      </note>
      <para>
       If you're using Apache 2, especially with something like RedHat, you may
       need to edit another directive, <literal>LimitRequestBody</literal>, as
       described in <ulink url="http://gallery.menalto.com/index.php?name=PNphpBB2&amp;file=viewtopic&amp;t=7419">
       this forum post</ulink>.  Setting this directive to 0 (i.e. <literal>
       LimitRequestBody 0</literal>) will allow you to upload as big a file as
       you want (until you hit <literal>upload_max_filesize</literal> and/or
       <literal>post_max_size</literal> -- see the above email link for more
       information).
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
   
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.7">
     <question>
      <para>
       When I try to run <command>configure.sh</command>, I get an error like this:
       <literal>chmod: getting attributes of `setup\r': No such file or directory</literal>
       How do I fix that?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       The answer is to simply upload the <filename>configure.sh</filename> file
       in <literal>ASCII FTP mode</literal>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.8">
     <question>
      <para>
       When I try to click on the "[login]" link on the Gallery page, nothing happens
       (no window pops up).  What's wrong?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       The most common reason for this is that you have JavaScript disabled or limited
       in your browser.  Make sure that JavaScript is allowed to open windows, or else
       you may not be able to login to Gallery.
      </para>
      <para>
       The number two reason for this problem is that your login page has a
       slightly different hostname than the one you used for your gallery.
       You can check this by right clicking on the login page and selecting
       Properties to see what its URL is. The common cause for this is that you
       used a variation on the standard URL to get to your Gallery, and then the
       browser thinks that the JavaScript popup is actually on a different host
       and it causes a security exception when the popup tries to control the
       main window. For example, if you've told Gallery in the config wizard that
       your gallery is at http://www.menalto.com/photos and then you actually
       access the Gallery by going to http://menalto.com/photos
       (note the "www" is missing), you'll still see your Gallery, but you'll
       experience this problem. The solution is to pick one hostname and stick
       with it.  
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.9">
     <question>
      <para>
       When I try to login, everything seems to go correctly, but Gallery doesn't
       log me in?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       There could be a few reasons why this doesn't work.  Here are some of them
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         If you are on Windows, you need to edit your <literal>session.save_path
         </literal> directive in &php.ini; to a valid directory.
          This defaults to <filename>/tmp</filename> which isn't a valid directory
          on Windows.  Change it to a valid temp folder, such as
          <filename>c:\winnt\temp</filename>.  Then restart your webserver.
        </para>
        <para>
         If you don't have access to &php.ini;, add this to the
         &htaccess; file in your gallery directory.
         <screen>
          php_value session.save_path "c:\winnt\temp"
         </screen>
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Locate the temporary directory specified in php.ini, or as specified
         in the paragraph above, and remove the sess_* files.  If Apache/PHP leave stale
         session files in the temporary directory, errors can occur when trying to
         create the session, and not logging in is the symptom.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Make sure that the <literal>session.use_cookies</literal> setting is on
         in &php.ini;.  It defaults to on, but your host may
         have turned it off.  You can verify the setting by putting Gallery into
         configuration mode and visiting the <filename>setup/phpinfo.php</filename>
         page in your browser.  Search for that directive.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Verify that it is not <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.8">FAQ C.8
         </link>
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Verify that your browser is configured to accept cookies.  If you have
         this functionality turned off, please turn it back on, or Gallery will
         not work.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Put Gallery back into configuration mode and visit the <filename>setup/
         session_test.php</filename> script.  Refresh the page and see if the
         number increases.  If it doesn't, you have a problem with sessions.  If you
         have done all of the above steps, you may need to contact your host for
         help.
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Ensure that you are logging in using the same URL that you specified during
         Gallery's configuration.  If your host responds to "www.myhost.com" and "myhost.com",
         you need to use the one that is specified in your configuration.  If you use the one
         that's not specified, you may be unable to login.  Another remedy for this issue is
         to follow the instructions in <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.22">FAQ C.22</link>
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>   

    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.10">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I see <literal>Warning: Undefined variable: GALLERY_BASEDIR...
       </literal> at the top of the page?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Gallery 1.x generates a ton of warnings. We're fixing this in the next
       release. In the meantime, you need to turn down the error reporting level
       in your &php.ini; file so that you don't see these
       warnings. You can do that by setting error_reporting = E_ALL &amp; ~E_NOTICE
       in &php.ini;. Then restart your Apache server.     
      </para>
      <para>
       If you don't see a change after doing this, it's possible that you're
       editing the wrong php.ini file. Go to <filename>gallery/setup/phpinfo.php
       </filename> in your web browser and it will tell you (near the top of the
       file) where it thinks your &php.ini; file is located.
       After making the change, phpinfo() should say that your error_reporting
       level is "2039".
      </para>
      <para>
       You can also add this line to your &htaccess; file
       <screen>
        php_value error_reporting 2039
       </screen>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.11">
     <question>
      <para>
       I can successfully upload photos, but when I look in my album all I see
       are broken image icons. Why?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       You've specified an incorrect path to your albums directory in the config
       wizard.  You can fix this by re-running the config wizard and correcting
       the Albums URL value or you can edit the &config.php;
       file and fix the $gallery-&gt;app-&gt;albumDirURL variable. 
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.12">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get <literal>Failed opening 'html_wrap/inline_albumthumb.header.default'</literal>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       If you unzipped/untarred the Gallery script on a Mac running OS 9.2.1
       or less (ie, non OS X), once its uploaded, three files need to be renamed.
       They are in the HTML_Wrap folder - <filename>inline_albumthumb.footer.default
       </filename>, <filename>inline_albumthumb.header.default</filename>, and
       <filename>inline_gallerythumb.frame.default</filename>. The last few
       characters at the end of these file names will get truncated on the Mac
       so Gallery won't be able to find them (there will be an error message
       above and below each photo). Adding the 't' at the end in FTP or Telnet
       will solve this. This is only a problem if its untarred/gzipped on a Mac.
       If they are unzipped on the server they will work fine. [Thanks James
       O'Donnell]
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.13">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I see this error:
       <screen>
        jpegtopnm: WRITING PPM FILE
        option `--quality' doesn't allow an argument?
       </screen>
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This problem is caused by one of two things:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         You have safe mode enabled.  Gallery can't run in this environment.  See
         <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.5">FAQ C.5</link> for more information
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Your NetPBM binaries have a bug.  Please use the NetPBM binaries found
         on the Gallery Download Page.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.14"> 
     <question>
      <para>
       Why, when I try to upload images, does it say <literal>No images uploaded
       </literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This can be caused by one of two things:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.6">FAQ C.6</link>
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Your PHP configuration has file uploads disabled. Put Gallery in config
         mode and open <filename>gallery/setup/phpinfo.php</filename> in your
         web browser and search for the <literal>file_uploads</literal> row. If
         <literal>file_uploads</literal> isn't enabled, then you won't be able
         to upload images to Gallery, and you should talk to your system
         administrator.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.15">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get this error: <literal>Warning: fopen(".../albums/team/album.dat.lock","a+")</literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This typically happens when your ISP makes a change in your environment
       (like upgrading PHP or moving things around) without telling you about it.
       In a nutshell, some of Gallery's files wind up being owned by the wrong
       user and their permissions become set such that Gallery can no longer
       write to them. I've never found this to be the result of a bug in Gallery.
       To fix this, you can change the permissions on your Gallery data files
       so that Apache can read the files again. This should only happen on Unix.
       If you have shell access, you can fix it like this:
       <screen>
        cd /path/to/albums
        cd ..
        chmod -R 777 albums
       </screen>
      </para>
      <para>
       If you don't have shell access, you can use your FTP client to <emphasis>
       recursively (every file and every directory)</emphasis> chmod the albums
       directory 777.  <emphasis>Make sure you chmod the <filename>.users</filename>
       directory, which can sometimes be hidden from view.  See <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.19">
       FAQ C.19</link> for more details</emphasis>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.16">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get the error <literal>Allowed memory size of Xxx bytes exhausted
       </literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       [answered by Vallimar] You are exhausting the available memory that PHP
       has access to. In &php.ini; there is a config variable
       named <literal>memory_limit</literal> that by default is set to 8MB. I
       quickly exhausted this after uploading a couple thousand images and had
       to increase it.  Edit &php.ini; and increase it to a larger
       value (restart Apache afterwards).  If you don't have access to <filename>
       php.ini</filename>, you can add this line to your &htaccess;
       file.
       <screen>
        php_value memory_limit [new memory limit]
       </screen>
       <note>
        <simpara>
         When adding that line to &htaccess;, you must use a 
         number, in bytes.  For example, 8MB would be about 8000000 bytes.
        </simpara>
       </note>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>  

    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.17">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get <literal>pnmtojpeg: No such file or directory when uploading
       images</literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       In version 9.19 of NetPBM, they changed the name of the <command>ppmtojpeg
       </command> binary to <command>pnmtojpeg</command>. It's the same binary
       and serves the same purpose, but it's got a different name. The precompiled
       binaries provided on the Gallery download page come with <command>ppmtojpeg
       </command>. The newer stuff that you might get comes with <command>pnmtojpeg
       </command>. Gallery tries really hard to figure out which one you have
       available and use it. However, security restrictions can make it impossible
       for us to tell for sure. So, it's possible that you have one version of the
       binary and Gallery expects the other. There are several easy solutions
       (you only need to do one of these):
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Copy <command>ppmtojpeg</command> to <command>pnmtojpeg</command>
         (or vice versa, as the case may be).
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Edit your &config.php; and change 
         $gallery-&gt;app-&gt;pnmtojpeg to <literal>"ppmtojpeg"</literal>
        (or <literal>"pnmtojpeg"</literal>, whichever you have).
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Upgrade to Gallery v1.3.4 which lets you specify which one you have in
         the config wizard.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>  

    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.18">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get this warning: <literal>Your script possibly relies on a
       session side-effect which existed until PHP 4.2.3</literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       In PHP 4.2.3, they made a change to the way that the session code works
       that results in PHP generating a warning when a session is created.
       In order to resolve this, we have to update some code in Gallery.
       This warning has no effect, except that it shows up on screen. You can
       make it go away by editing your php.ini and setting
       <screen>
        session.bug_compat_warn to <literal>off</literal>
       </screen>
       and restart Apache.
      </para>
      <para>
       If you don't have access to &php.ini;, add this line
       to your &htaccess;
       <screen>
        php_flag session.bug_compat_warn off
       </screen>
      </para>
      <para>
       This should be fixed in future versions of Gallery.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.19">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why, when I try to upload a &htaccess; and chmod it with my FTP client,
       it "disappears"?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This is because on some FTP clients, the default setting is to hide files
       that begin with a dot. The file may actually be on the server, but your
       FTP client isn't programmed to display it. To make these files
       "reappear", you must change some settings. PixelPoet has written a
       tutorial for WS_FTP available here:
       <ulink url="http://www.eclecticpixels.com/tutorials/chmod/">Quick Tips
       for Chmod with WS_FTP</ulink>.  If you use CuteFTP, see
       <ulink url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=phpBB_14&amp;file=index&amp;topic=701&amp;action=viewtopic&amp;topic=1902">
       this thread in the forums.</ulink>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.20">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why does uploading pictures on my RedHat 8.0 system result in an error
       or scewed picture?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       In RedHat 8.0, the default web server is Apache 2.0. Unfortunately, PHP
       and Apache 2 aren't very stable together yet, though current versions of
       PHP and Apache 2 do work relatively well together. However, there is a bug
       in the version of PHP distributed with RedHat 8.0 that can corrupt uploads.
       For information on how to fix these errors or scewed pictures, see
       <ulink url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=phpBB_14&amp;file=index&amp;action=viewtopic&amp;topic=4662">     
       this thread in the forums</ulink>.  Keep in mind that these are merely
       workarounds.  The best option is to upgrade your PHP version to the latest
       from <ulink url="http://www.php.net/">http://www.php.net/</ulink>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.21">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why doesn't Gallery work correctly on my RedHat 9.0 system?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       As in Red Hat Linux versions since 8.0, the default web server is Apache
       2. Apache 2.0 uses a totally different module API, making it necessary
       to rewrite all modules for this new version. Unfortunately, the PHP
       version that Red Hat 9.0 is distributed with has a very buggy interface
       with Apache 2.0. Some of these bugs have been fixed with the latest
       version of PHP. Please download the latest version from
       <ulink url="http://www.php.net/">http://www.php.net/</ulink>.  See
       <ulink url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=phpBB_14&amp;file=index&amp;action=viewtopic&amp;topic=5741&amp;1">
       this forum post</ulink> for information on how to compile PHP.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.22">
     <question>
      <para>
       How do I use Gallery both from inside my LAN and the internet?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <note>
       <simpara>
        There is a fix planned for future versions of Gallery to allow the config
        wizard to use relative URLs.  Stay tuned.
       </simpara>
      </note>
      <para>
       There are two ways to do this; both are shown below:
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The easiest way to do this is to use relative URLs in &config.php;.
          <note>
           <simpara>
            You will have to redo this each time you run the config wizard, since
            the config wizard won't accept relative urls.
           </simpara>
          </note>
          You need to edit &config.php; manually. There are two URLs in that file. Change each of them as follows:
         </para>
         <para>
          From:
          <literal>http://www.example.com/gallery</literal>
          <literal>http://www.example.com/gallery/albums</literal>
          To:
          <literal>/gallery</literal>
          <literal>/gallery/albums</literal>
          (change these URL's to match your Gallery setup)
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The second method does not require any server-side changes, as the changes you
          make are made on the client.  This may not be the most efficent solution, especially
          if you have many client computers.
         </para>
         <para>
          You need to edit a file called HOSTS on your client machine. The HOSTS file is a ip-address to
          domain-name mapping file.  Adding a line to this file, will make your client look for a local
          ip instead of an external ip, even if you use a fully qualified domain name.
         </para>
         <para>
          Add a line similar to this:
          <screen>
           10.0.0.2	example.com www.example.com
          </screen>
         </para>
         <para>
          This line will make all requests to example.com (and www.example.com) request the server at
          10.0.0.2 (replace this with your server's real LAN IP address).
         </para>
         <para>
          Depending on your client's operating system, the HOSTS file will be in a different place.
          Also note that on Windows clients, you will need to reboot the system for the changes
          to take place.
          <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
            <para>
             <emphasis>Windows 95/98/ME</emphasis> <filename>C:\windows\hosts</filename>
             <note>
              <simpara>
               By defaults this file in called <filename>hosts.sam</filename>.  It must
               be renamed <filename>hosts</filename> for everything to work.
              </simpara>
             </note>
            </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
            <para>
             <emphasis>Windows NT/2000/XP Pro</emphasis> <filename>c:\winnt\system32\drivers\etc\hosts</filename>
            </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
            <para>
             <emphasis>Windows XP Home</emphasis> <filename>c:\windows\system32\drivers\etc\hosts</filename>
            </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
            <para>
             <emphasis>Linux/Unix</emphasis> <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>
            </para>
           </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.23">
     <question>
      <para>
       I'm running Gallery 1.3.4, PHP 4.0.4 and I get <literal>Call to undefined
       function: array_search() in view_photo.php</literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This is a function that was introduced in PHP 4.0.5. You can upgrade your
       version of PHP, or if you prefer, make the following change to
       <filename>view_photo.php</filename>
      </para>
      <para>
       Insert the following at line 57 in view_photo.php
      </para>
      <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
if (!function_exists('array_search')) {
        function array_search($needle, $haystack) {
                for ($x=0; $x < sizeof($haystack); $x++) {
                        if ($haystack[$x] == $needle) {
                                return $x;
                        }
                }
                return NULL;
        }
}
]]>
      </programlisting>
      <note>
       <simpara>
        This has been fixed in Gallery 1.4.0
       </simpara>
      </note>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.24">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why, when I edit an album or photo's text, do quotation marks appear
       as <literal>\'</literal> (e.g. <literal>John Doe\'s Album</literal>)?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Your host has <literal>magic_quotes_gpc</literal> enabled in &php.ini;  This
       causes form variables with quotes to be escaped with backslashes.  Gallery
       tries to turn off this functionality, but in your case, this didn't succeed.
       You'll need to contact your host and ask them to turn this directive off, at
       least just for your site.
      </para>
      <note>
       <para>
        As of Gallery 1.4.0, Gallery will strip the slashes from fields so that
        this does not happen, even if <literal>magic_quotes_gpc</literal> is on.
       </para>
      </note>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.25">
     <question>
      <para>
       I can't extract a <literal>.tar.gz</literal> file on my Windows machine.
       Why not?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       You need to use WinZip <emphasis>twice</emphasis>. (WinZip is a bit weird
       when it comes to <literal>.tar.gz</literal> archives).
       <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Unzip, with WinZip, like you have done.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Rename the extracted file (in this example,
          <filename>netpbm1.1-gallery1.0-linux2.2-redhat6.2-intel</filename>)
          from <filename>netpbm1.1-gallery1.0-linux2.2-redhat6.2-intel</filename>
          to <filename>netpbm1.1-gallery1.0-linux2.2-redhat6.2-intel.tar</filename>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Unzip once more
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.26">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get an <literal>EOF / read error reading magic number</literal>
       error when uploading pictures with NetPBM?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Please see <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.2">FAQ c.2</link>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.27">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get errors like this: <literal>Warning: open_basedir restriction in effect. File is in wrong
       directory in /home/johndoe/public_html/gallery/platform/fs_unix.php on line 53</literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This is caused by a PHP directive called
       <ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/features.safe-mode.php#ini.open-basedir">open_basedir</ulink>.
       Basically, your host has misconfigured this directive and not added the directory where Gallery
       is located to the directories where PHP can access and modify files.  You'll need to contact them
       and ask them to add the directory where your website files are located.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.28">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get this error: <literal>Warning: write failed: No space left on device (28) in Unknown on line 0</literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Your host setup a quota for the web server user.  Though <emphasis>your account</emphasis> may still have
       space left, the quota for the web server user has been overrun.  Basically, you'll need to contact
       your host and ask them to cleanup the filesystem and/or adjust the quota.  If you are your host,
       adjust the quota using <command>edquota</command>.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.29">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get this error: <literal>Warning:  exec() has been disabled for security reasons</literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Basically, this is a form of safe mode.  Gallery requires functions like <literal>exec()</literal> to
       perform operations on images.  The steps to "fix" this problem are the same as in
       <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.5">FAQ C.5</link>.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.30">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why can't I upload images using ImageMagick on FreeBSD?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       The default install of ImageMagick on FreeBSD doesn't seem to compile with some
       important image support (e.g. JPEG), so you must explicitly tell it to.
       There are two ways of doing this.
       <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Compile ImageMagick using this command:
          <command>
           cd /usr/ports/graphics/ImageMagick/ &amp;&amp; make -DWITH_JPEG -DWITH_TIFF -DWITH_PNG
           install clean
          </command>
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Add the following lines to <filename>/etc/make.conf</filename>:
          <screen>
           WITH_JPEG=yes
           WITH_TIFF=yes
           WITH_PNG=yes 
          </screen>
          Then uninstall ImageMagick via ports (<command>make deinstall clean</command>)
          and reinstall it (<command>make install clean</command>)
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.31">
     <question>
      <para>
       How do I put my Gallery into debug mode?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       There are two ways, each pretty much equal in simplicity.
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Put your Gallery into <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">
          configuration mode</link>.  On Step 2, there will be an option to
          turn on debug mode.  Make sure this is "on" and complete the wizard.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Edit &config.php; manually (use the first option if you are not 
          comfortable modifying PHP files yourself).  Change this line
          <screen>
           $gallery-&gt;app-&gt;debug = "no";
          </screen>
          to
          <screen>
           $gallery-&gt;app-&gt;debug = "yes";
          </screen>
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
       Sometimes it is also helpful to enable <literal>devMode</literal>.  Find this line in &config.php;
       <screen>
        $gallery->app->devMode = "no";
       </screen>
       And change "no" to "yes"  This will enable some extra debugging features and turn up PHP's
       error reporting level.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.32">
     <question>
      <para>
       I have uploaded the NetPBM or ImageMagick binaries to my site, but
       I don't know the absolute path to specify in the configuration
       wizard.  What do I do?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Upload a file named <filename>test.php</filename> to your
       NetPBM or ImageMagick directory.  The contents of this file should
       be
       <screen>
<![CDATA[
<?php
print getcwd ();
?>
]]>
       </screen>
       View this file via the web (for example: http://www.example.com/gallery/
       netpbm/test.php).  It will tell you the absolute path to specify.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.33">
     <question>
      <para>
       When I try to enter an album, I get a 404 error.  What's up?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       One of two things in happening
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
	 <para>
	  The Gallery URL you specified during the configuration wizard
	  is incorrect.  Verify that the value you specified does indeed
	  point to where Gallery is installed.
	 </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	 <para>
	  <emphasis role="bold">mod_rewrite</emphasis> is not working.  Edit
	  your &config.php; file and change this line:
	  <screen>
	   $gallery->app->feature["rewrite"] = 1;
	  </screen>
	  to
	  <screen>
	   $gallery->app->feature["rewrite"] = 0;
	  </screen>          
          Voila!  The URLs should work correctly now.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.34">
     <question>
      <para>
       I changed a value on Step 3 of the configuration wizard (or in
       &config.php;), but the change isn't taking effect.  What's going on?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       These values are <emphasis>defaults</emphasis>.  They take effect for
       new top-level albums, but do not affect already existing albums.
       If you want to change the value of these parameters for already
       existing albums, edit each album's properties.  You can access album
       properties by logging in as admin and going into the album in question.
       Select "properties" from the &lt;&lt;admin options&gt;&gt; pulldown.
       Then, in the popup window you will be able to change the properties
       for that album.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.35">
     <question>
      <para>
       Can I host images on another server to conserve space?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       The straight answer is no.  Gallery must have the images on the local
       server in order to manipulate (i.e. resize, rotate, etc..) them.  There
       is no fast, easy, and widely available way to manipulate (i.e. edit) files
       on remote servers (there are a few, but none fit all 3 criteria).
      </para>
      <para>
       It <emphasis>is possible</emphasis>, however, to host your images on multiple
       servers in order to distribute the bandwidth.  For instance, if you have a server
       that doesn't support PHP, but has lots of bandwidth, you can host the images
       on that server (<emphasis>as well as the local server</emphasis>) and Gallery
       will attempt to use the images on the server with lots of bandwidth, so that
       the local server doesn't suffer so much.  More information is available in the
       <link linkend="gallery1-admin.mirroring">mirroring tutorial</link>.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
     
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.36">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get errors with email on Windows?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       If you go to http://www.example.com/gallery/setup/check_mail.php and it gives you the following
       errors:
       </para>
       <para>
        <screen>
         "Error! sendmail_path not set"
         and/or 
         "Error! SMTP not set"
         </screen>
         you will have to do some changes to your php installation.
         If you get the "Error! sendmail_path not set" you can safely ignore it on Windows, since
         it disregards the sendmail_path anyway.
         To fix the other potential problem, locate your php.ini 
         (probably under C:\Program Files\php or C:\windows), open it with a texteditor
         and find "[mail function]".
       </para>
       <para>
        It should look something like this:
        <screen>
         [mail function]
         ; For Win32 only.
         SMTP = 
         ; For Win32 only.
        sendmail_from = 
        ; For Unix only.  You may supply arguments as well (default: 'sendmail -t -i').
        ;sendmail_path =
        </screen>
       Change SMTP to whatever smtp-server you can use that doesn't need authentication
       and sendmail_from to an email address.
       Example:
        <screen>
         SMTP = smtp.server.com
         sendmail_from = youremail@server.com
        </screen>
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.37">
     <question>
      <para>
       I've forgotten my admin password!  How can I reset it?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Version 1.4.3 or below: Resetting your admin password is easy; 
       just set your Gallery into config mode, rerun the <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">
       configuration wizard</link> and specify a new password on step 2.
      </para>
      <para>
       Version 1.4.4 and above:
       <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
	 <para>Create a file named <screen>resetadmin</screen> in your /gallery/setup directory.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>Visit the <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">configuration wizard</link> in your browser</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>Follow the instructions on the page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>Specify a new password in step 2 of the configuration wizard</para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
       The config wizard will give you a special piece of information,
       and you will be required to edit the <emphasis>resetadmin</emphasis> file,
       add the string, save, and refresh your browser.  This is a security measure to prove that you
       are an administrator.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
     
     <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.38">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why are my picture frames screwed up?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       If you have a file called gallery/css/embedded_style.css (ie
       without the ".default" ending) you should update it.  Download your
       version, open it in Notepad, and cut and paste the contents of
       gallery/css/embedded_style.css.diff to the end.  You can configure
       the new classes if you want to, and then upload the new version to
       your website.
      </para>
      <para>
       You do not need to make any changes to standalone.css.
       Since version 1.4.1 Gallery also has configurable image frames.  
       If you have customized frames for your images, they should still work 
       with 1.4.1.
      </para>
      <para>
       However, if you would like to use the new frames, you will need to
       remove the following files, as appropriate:
       <screen>
        html_wrap/inline_albumthumb.frame   html_wrap/inline_photo.frame
        html_wrap/inline_gallerythumb.frame html_wrap/inline_photothumb.frame
        html_wrap/inline_moviethumb.frame
       </screen>
      </para>
      <para>
       If you didn't touch the CSS or frame files, this probably means that
       you didn't override the files upon upgrade.  Make sure that your FTP
       client overrides the old files and upgrades to the new ones.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.39">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get this error: <literal>Fatal error: session_start(): Failed to
       initialize storage module: user...</literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Some other application has setup PHP to use a user-defined session handler.
       Gallery, however, doesn't run its own handler and relies on PHP to handle
       things.  To correct for this, add this line to the end of your &htaccess;
       file:
       <screen>
        php_value session.save_handler "files"
       </screen>
       This should fix it if you host allows you to edit PHP directives in &htaccess;.
       If not, you may need to contact them to get it changed globally.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.c.40">
     <question>
      <para>
       I need to remove my albums directory, but I can't since the webserver user
       owns the files.  What can I do?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       Bharat has made a simple script to chmod all the files in your albums directory
       0777, so you can easily delete them with your FTP client.  Download his script
       here: <ulink url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=Downloads&amp;file=index&amp;req=viewdownload&amp;cid=6">
       Gallery Utilities</ulink> ("Bharat's Cleanup Script").  Instructions are included
       in the top of the file.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
   </qandadiv>
  
  </qandaset>

 </sect2>
  
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.faq.d" ischunk="yes">
  <title>D. Migrating Gallery</title>

  <qandaset>
   
   <qandadiv label="D">
   
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.d.1">
     <question>
      <para>
       How can I migrate my Gallery from one host to another?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <warning>
       <para>
        If you are moving between a Windows and non-Windows host, please
	make sure your Gallery is upgraded to at least version 1.4
	<emphasis>before</emphasis> you attempt to migrate
       </para>
      </warning>
      <para>
       The important data that needs to be saved is your albums directory.
       You only need to save the actual Gallery files if you modified them.
      </para>
      <para>
       To move your Gallery from one server to another, you must move your old
       albums directory to the new host. To do this, either download the albums
       directory via FTP (if you are using FTP) or use a utility like tar and/or
       gzip/bzip (or zip) to make an archive of the albums directory (you can
       only use the command line utilities if you have shell access). Note that
       Gallery creates a <filename>.users</filename> folder in the albums
       directory, which can be hidden by some FTP clients. This directory is
       vital if you want to maintain your user database. See
       <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.19">FAQ C.19</link> if your
       FTP client hides this directory and you can't download it. Once you have
       a copy of the albums directory, upload it to your new host. If you used
       FTP, just re-upload the albums directory to your new host. If you used 
       something like tar, upload the archive to the new host and untar/unzip it.
       Once you have the albums directory on the new host, you must chmod all the
       files and directories 0777 (recursively) (see FAQ <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.15">
       C.15</link> for information). If you do not chmod the files correctly,
       your new Gallery will not work correctly.
      </para>
      <para>
       If you wish, you can also save your old &config.php;
       file and upload it instead of creating a new, blank &config.php;
       (as you would with a normal installation) before configuring
       your new Gallery installation. You'll still have to re-run the
       configuration wizard to specify new paths for everything, but saving
       some host-independent information (e.g. album defaults, etc..) can save
       you some time.
      </para>
      <para>
       After you have your old albums directory on the new server, you should
       download a copy of Gallery and upload it just as you would install any
       other copy of Gallery (see the README file for installation instructions).
       However, when you get to the configuration wizard, for the
       'Albums Directory' configuration parameter, you should put the path to
       the albums directory you just uploaded, not a blank directory, as you
       would on a clean install of Gallery. After you secure Gallery, all your
       data should show up intact!
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.d.2">
     <question>
      <para>
       Why do I get this error after migration: <literal>Warning: fopen
       ('.../albums/foo/album.dat.lock', 'a+')</literal>?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       This is caused by not recursively chmodding the new albums directory 0777.
       See FAQ <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.15">C.15</link> for information
       on how to fix this.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.d.3">
     <question>
      <para>
       Will moving my Gallery to another host cause me to lose data
       (comment, images, etc..)?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       If you follow the instructions in <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.d.1">FAQ D.1
       </link>, there should be no lose of data whatsoever. However, because of Murphy's
       law, it's a good idea not to delete your albums directory on your old host before
       you know everything is working on the new host.
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    
    <qandaentry id="gallery1-install.faq.d.4">
     <question>
      <para>
       Something went wrong, it's not working! What do I do?
      </para>
     </question>
     <answer>
      <para>
       First, try again. Make sure you follow all the instructions in
       <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.d.1">FAQ D.1</link>.
       If you still cannot get it to work, start a thread in the forums. As with
       any forum post, include as much detail as possible -- exactly what you did
       (don't just say 'I followed FAQ D.1'), what you expected to happen, and
       what really happened, along with any error messages. We will probably be
       able to sort you out!
      </para>
     </answer>
    </qandaentry> 
    
   </qandadiv>
   
  </qandaset>
   
 </sect2>    

</sect1>
