<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-install.required-programs">
 <title>Installing Required Programs</title>
 
 <para>
  Gallery, being PHP, cannot do all of the complex image operations required to
  resize and otherwise manipulate images by itself.  It requires other programs
  to be able to do this, and you must install these programs or Gallery cannot
  work.
 </para>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.required-programs.netpbm">
  <title>NetPBM (required)</title>

  <para>
   NetPBM is easy to install yourself. You can grab the files from
   the <ulink
   url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php&#63;group_id=7130">Gallery
   Download Page</ulink>. You do not need root access; just upload
   the <filename>NetPBM</filename> files via your FTP client (in
   <emphasis>binary</emphasis> mode) and <function>CHMOD</function>
   the directory and all the files in that directory with the
   following permissions: 755. If the configuration wizard can't
   locate the <filename>NetPBM</filename> directory it will ask you
   for the exact location and you can fill in the correct path.
  </para>
  <note>
   <simpara>
    NetPBM is not required if you are using ImageMagick.
   </simpara>
  </note>
 </sect2>
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.required-programs.imagemagick">
  <title>ImageMagick (required)</title>

  <para>
   ImageMagick is an alternative for NetPBM.  It is usually considered to be
   faster, but can be more difficult to install.  As with NetPBM, you don't
   need root access to install the binaries.  You can download ImageMagick
   builds from <ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org/">http://www.imagemagick.org
   </ulink>.  Also as with NetPBM, the binaries must be chmodded 0755 (including
   the directory they are in).
  </para>
  <note>
   <simpara>
    ImageMagick is not required if you are using NetPBM.
   </simpara>
  </note>
 </sect2>
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.required-programs.jhead">
  <title>Jhead (Optional)</title>
  
  <para>
   If you want to display the EXIF information that many digital
   cameras store in JPEG images, you'll need to install a small
   program called <filename>Jhead</filename> to your webspace. A few
   hosts have begun having it pre-installed for Gallery users. If you
   are installing Jhead yourself you can install it either in the
   <filename>gallery</filename> directory or in your
   <filename>public_html</filename> directory (sometimes called
   <filename>www</filename> or something similar). If you don't need
   to display the exif information for your photos, skip this
   step.
  </para>
  <para>
   Download the pre-built executable and upload it to your webspace
   via FTP, making sure that you upload it in
   <emphasis>BINARY</emphasis> mode. If Windows has saved it with a
   <filename>.txt</filename> extension, simply remove the extension
   once you've uploaded it and call the file
   <filename>jhead</filename> (with no file
   extension). <function>CHMOD</function> this file to 755. You will
   have to fill in the path to the Jhead file when you run the
   configuration wizard.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can download the correct build for your webspace and find out
   more information here: <ulink
   url="http://www.sentex.net/~mwandel/jhead/">http://www.sentex.net/~mwandel/jhead/</ulink>
  </para>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.required-programs.jpegtran">
  <title>JpegTRAN (optional)</title>
  
  <note>
   <simpara>
    JpegTRAN support added in 1.4.0
   </simpara>
  </note>
  
  <para>
   JpegTRAN is a utility to allow Gallery perform lossless rotation on JPEG
   images.  This results in a better quality rotation, as well as a speed
   increase, according to some.
  </para>
  <para>
   JpegTRAN is incredibly easy to install, and is usually included in most
   distributions.  JpegTRAN is usually included in the <literal>libjpeg</literal>
   or <literal>libjpeg-progs</literal> package.  Simply install this package
   on your system, and (re)-run the <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">
   configuration wizard</link> and specify the path to JpegTRAN.
  </para>
  <para>
   For Windows, JpegTRAN can be downloaded from
   <ulink url="http://www.sf.net/projects/gnuwin32">the GNU Win32 project</ulink>.
   It is in the <literal>jpeg</literal> package, specifically the <literal>jpeg-bin</literal>
   package.  Download the file and unzip it in a directory (<command>jpegtran</command>
   will be in the <filename>bin/</filename> directory), then specify the full
   path to it in the config wizard.
  </para>
 </sect2>
   
</sect1>
