<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-install.requirements">
 <title>Installation Requirements</title>
  
 <note>
  <para>
   For information on installing all the required programs, along with other
   optional programs that can enhance Gallery, see the
   <link linkend="gallery1-install.required-programs">installing required programs</link>
   guide.
  </para>
 </note> 

 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.requirements.required">
  <title>Required Items</title>
  
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org/">Apache</ulink> 1.x, 2.x or <ulink url="http://www.zeus.com/products/zws/">Zeus</ulink> web server
    </para>
    <para>
     Our primary development and testing is on the Apache web server on
     Unix. Our user base includes:
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Apache 1.x and 2.x on Linux, FreeBSD, Solaris, HP-UX, NetBSD,
        OpenBSD, Mac OS X
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Zeus Web Server on Linux and HP-UX 11
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Apache 1.x and 2.x on Windows 2000, Windows NT and Windows XP
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>
     Users have experienced a great deal of difficulty getting Gallery
     to run properly on Win95, Win98, WinME or using IIS4.0/5.0.  As a
     result, we <emphasis>do not support</emphasis> those platforms.
    </para>
    
    <para>
     <emphasis>Apache2 Note:</emphasis> The first correctly functioning
     version of PHP on Apache2 is PHP 4.3.0.  If you're having problems
     on Apache2 and you're not running PHP 4.3.0, you must upgrade (or
     ask your host to upgrade), until then we cannot help you.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.php.net/">PHP</ulink> 4
    </para>
    <para>
     PHP is a web server module that allows you to create applications
     using an embedded scripting language. If you don't yet have a web
     host and are looking for one, check their site to see what their
     features and software include. If you don't see PHP listed, write
     and ask if they support PHP (while you are at it, make sure they
     run it with <function>safe mode</function> OFF). You need PHP to
     run Gallery.
    </para>
    <para>
     Run your own server? If you're on a Unix box, the odds are good
     that you'll be able to download PHP easily in either source or
     binary form for your system. As of this writing, Gallery requires
     PHP version 4.0.4pl1 or more recent. It has been tested on
     versions of PHP up to 4.3.4
    </para>
    <para>
     <emphasis>PLEASE NOTE</emphasis>: Your PHP installation
     <emphasis>must not be in <function>safe
     mode</function></emphasis>. Gallery is a sophisticated
     application and its operations require extensive privileges. Safe
     mode prevents Gallery from functioning properly.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     mod_rewrite (optional)
    </para>
    <para>
     mod_rewrite is an Apache module that lets web server applications
     do clever things with URLs. Gallery uses this module to allow it
     to use short URLs. In other words, you see this:
     <blockquote>
      <para>
       http://www.example.com/photos/cole-earlydays/aga
      </para>
     </blockquote>
     instead of this:
     <blockquote>
      <para>
       http://www.example.com/photos/view_photo.php&#63;set_albumName=cole-earlydays&amp;id=aga
      </para>
     </blockquote>
     Obviously the shorter one is easier to remember and nicer to use
     when sending links to friends and family. Unfortunately, if you
     don't own the web server then it may be difficult or impossible to
     enable mod_rewrite, but you can always write your host and ask.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <ulink url="http://netpbm.sourceforge.net/">NetPBM</ulink> or
     <ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org/">ImageMagick</ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
     Gallery requires an image manipulation program to do certain operations
     with images.  Please install either NetPBM or ImageMagick before trying
     to install Gallery.  See this <link linkend="gallery1-install.required-programs">
     installation guide</link> for information.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.requirements.whatyouhave">
  <title>How to find out what you have</title>
  
  <para>
   To find out which version of Apache and PHP is installed on your
   webspace (or server), use the <filename>phpinfo.php</filename> file
   in the setup directory of Gallery to display this information, by
   typing the following in your browser window:
   
   <blockquote>
    <para>
     http://www.example.com/gallery/setup/phpinfo.php
    </para>
   </blockquote>
   
   This file is accessible only when Gallery is still in configure
   mode (or freshly copied to the server).
  </para>
 </sect2>

</sect1>
