<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-install.requirements">
 <title>Installation Requirements</title>
 
 <warning>
  <para>
   Please look through these requirements <emphasis>before</emphasis> attempting
   to install Gallery!
  </para>
 </warning>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.requirements.wwwserver">
  <title>Web Server</title>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-install.requirements.wwwserver.apache">
   <title>Apache</title>
   
   <para>
    Apache is the preferred web server for a Gallery installation.  It's free,
    open source and available from <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org">the Apache
    project's website</ulink>.  Apache runs on many different operating systems,
    including BSD, Linux, and Windows.
   </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-install.requirements.wwwserver.iis">
   <title>Microsoft IIS</title>
   
   <para>
    Gallery is known to run under Microsoft's web server, Internet Information
    Services, though the Gallery team doesn't offically support it.  In almost
    all cases, though, you will need administrative privileges on the server
    to install Gallery under IIS.
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.requirements.php">
  <title>PHP</title>
  
  <para>
   Gallery is written in PHP, a language specifically crafted for web-based
   applications.  PHP is available freely from <ulink url="http://www.php.net">
   http://www.php.net</ulink>.  PHP can be installed under Apache or IIS; installation
   procedures are available through PHP's <ulink url="http://www.php.net/install">
   documentation</ulink>
  </para>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-install.requirements.php.settings">
   <title>Settings</title>
   
   <para>
    In addition to just a PHP installation, Gallery requires certain PHP directives
    or settings to be set a certain way.  In most cases, Gallery will run under
    default settings, but if you host has changed some directives, it can affect
    the way Gallery runs.
   </para>
   
   <para>
    To check the status of your PHP settings, navigate to http://www.example.com/gallery/setup/phpinfo.php,
    where http://www.example.com/gallery is where you have uncompressed Gallery.
    Search for the following directives and make sure they are set appropriately.
   
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis>safe_mode</emphasis> - Safe mode <emphasis role="bold">must be
       disabled</emphasis>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis>disable_functions</emphasis> - <emphasis role="bold">exec()</emphasis>
       must not be listed in PHP's disable_functions directive
      </para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis>file_uploads</emphasis> - File uploads must be enabled (set to 'On')
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </para>
    
   <para>
    If any of those conditions are not met, Gallery <emphasis>will not work on
    your host</emphasis>
   </para>
    
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.requirements.imageprocessing">
  <title>Image Processing Library</title>
  
  <para>
   Gallery requires you to install NetPBM or ImageMagick in order for it to perform
   basic image operations (resize, rotate, crop, etc...).  It is possible that your
   host already has one of these two libraries installed (only one or the other
   is needed).  If not, you can download pre-compiled binaries for use on various
   systems from our <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=7130&amp;package_id=14464">
   download page</ulink>.  Just download the appropriate binaries that correspond
   to the architecure and operating system of your server and upload them to a folder
   in <emphasis>binary mode</emphasis> (if using FTP).
  </para>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.requirements.optional">
  <title>Optional Items</title>
  
  <para>
   Gallery has the ability to use several outside libraries and programs in order
   to enhance functionality, though these programs aren't required for a basic
   working Gallery
  </para>

  <sect3 id="gallery1-install.requirements.optional.modrewrite">
   <title>mod_rewrite</title>
   
   <para>
    mod_rewrite is an Apache module (not available on IIS installations) that allows
    Gallery to use shorter URLs for your albums.  For instance, using mod_rewrite,
    a URL referring to an album might appear like
    http://www.example.com/gallery/trip_to_spain, instead of a longer
    http://www.example.com/gallery/view_album.php?set_albumName=trip_to_spain
   </para>
   
   <para>
    mod_rewrite requires administrator access to install (if not previously enabled)
    and modification to the AllowOverride directive in httpd.conf.  More information
    is in <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/mod/mod_rewrite.html">the Apache
    documentation</ulink>
   </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-install.requirements.optional.jhead">
   <title>jhead</title>
   
   <para>
    jhead is a free tool that can be used to extract EXIF data from images, which
    most digital cameras now add to photos.  If enabled, EXIF data will be available
    for viewing by clicking on the [properties] link by individual images.
   </para>
   
   <para>
    More information can be found at the <ulink url="http://www.sentex.net/~mwandel/jhead/">
    jhead website</ulink>
   </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-install.requirements.optional.zip">
   <title>zipinfo</title>
   
   <para>
    zipinfo is a free tool that allows Gallery to unzip ZIP archives so that you
    can easily upload multiple photos.  If enabled, you will be able to upload
    a ZIP archive as you would any other single picture, and Gallery will add all
    the images in the archive.
   </para>
   
   <para>
    zipinfo can be obtained from the <ulink url="http://www.info-zip.org/pub/infozip/">
    Info-ZIP website</ulink>
   </para>
  </sect3>
  
  <sect3 id="gallery1-install.requirements.optional.jpegtran">
   <title>jpegtran</title>
   
   <para>
    jpegtran is a free tool that allows Gallery to loselessly rotate JPEG images.
    While NetPBM and ImageMagick can rotate JPEG images, jpegtran allows you
    to rotate images without risking degradation.
   </para>
   
   <para>
    More information can be found at the <ulink url="http://www.ijg.org/">Independent
    JPEG Group's website</ulink>
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
