<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-install.unix-ftp">
 <title>Installing on a Unix/Linux Server with FTP</title>
 
 &gallery1.upgrade;
 
 &gallery1.requirements;
 
 <para>
  Once unpacked (unzipped), you should have a directory called
  <filename>gallery</filename> that contains most of the files and
  directories required. Now you're ready to install your Gallery:
 </para>

 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Create two blank files in your favorite editor,(i.e.
    Notepad, Note Tab, Editplus, Crimson Editor, pico, vi, emacs, joe, etc..).
   </para>
   <para>
    Call one &htaccess; and the other
    &config.php;. Place these inside the Gallery
    directory.
   </para>
   <para>
    Upload the Gallery directory to your server using an FTP program
    (like WS_FTP, CuteFTP or Fetch). Upload all files except for image
    files in <emphasis>ASCII</emphasis> mode. Upload image files in
    <emphasis>binary</emphasis> mode. <emphasis>Keep the directory
    tree intact</emphasis>&#8212;you should see various folders INSIDE the
    Gallery folder, as well as the php pages that go together to run your
    Gallery site.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <emphasis>Create a directory on your webspace called
    <filename>albums</filename>.</emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>
    Gallery will use this directory to store the albums you create and
    the images you upload to those albums. This directory can reside
    inside the Gallery directory or outside the Gallery directory -
    your choice. <emphasis>Make note of where you create this
    directory.</emphasis>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You need to set permissions to make some of the files and
    directories writable. This involves using the
    <function>CHMOD</function> command. If you do not understand
    <function>CHMOD</function>, there are some resources and
    information listed at <ulink
    url="http://www.eclecticpixels.com/tutorials/chmod/">http://www.eclecticpixels.com/tutorials/chmod/</ulink>. Chmod
    as follows:
    <programlisting>
     chmod 777 albums (this is the album dir created in step 2)
     chmod 666 .htaccess
     chmod 666 config.php
     chmod 755 setup/ (setup/ is a directory)
    </programlisting>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Run the configuration wizard, as described in <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">this guide</link>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Enjoy your new Gallery!
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
</sect1>
