<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-install.upgrade">
 <title>Upgrading a Previous Gallery Installation</title>

 <para>
  This sections describes how to upgrade your Gallery from an old version to
  a new one.  Upgrading is very easy, and you won't lose any data if you
  follow all the directions.
 </para>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.upgrade.shell">
  <title>Upgrading with Shell Access</title>
  
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Put your Gallery into configuration mode</emphasis>.
     This is very important.  If you don't do this, then you won't be
     able to back up your existing setup directory or install the new
     setup code on top of it.
     <screen>
      cd gallery
      sh configure.sh (or configure.bat for Windows)
     </screen>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Make a backup of your old Gallery installation.  The easiest way to do
     this is to use the <command>tar</command> command.
     <screen>
      tar -cz gallery > gallery-backup.tar.gz
     </screen>
     On Windows, use something like WinZip to create an archive of your Gallery
     directory.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem> 
    <para>
     Download Gallery from the <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=7130">
     Gallery SF.net Download Page</ulink>.  Put the tarball in your gallery directory's
     parent directory.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Untar the new Gallery version over the old one.
     <screen>
      tar -xvzf gallery-1.x.x.tar.gz
      [list of new files]
     </screen>
     Windows users: use WinZip to extract Gallery over the old installation
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Re-run the <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">configuration
     wizard</link>.  Afterward, put Gallery back into secure mode, as described
     in that guide.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Some upgrades include changes to the Gallery data formats and
     require you to upgrade all of your albums.  You can either let
     this happen automatically the first time somebody views the
     album, or you can upgrade the albums yourself when logged in as
     an admin.  If you want to upgrade them all, open 
     <blockquote>
      <para>
       http://www.example.com/gallery/upgrade_album.php
      </para>
     </blockquote>
     in your web browser (use the real url to your Gallery, of course)
     and then follow the instructions you find there.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Enjoy your upgraded Gallery!
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.upgrade.ftp">
  <title>Upgrading Gallery with FTP</title>
  
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>Put your Gallery into configuration mode</emphasis>.
     This is very important.  If you don't do this, then you won't be
     able to back up your existing setup directory or install the new
     setup code on top of it.  Do this by chmodding &htaccess;
     and &config.php; 0777 and by chmodding the
     <filename>setup/</filename> directory 0755.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Make a backup copy of your Gallery directory.  Use your FTP client to download
     the old Gallery directory, just in case
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem> 
    <para>
     Download Gallery from the <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=7130">
     Gallery SF.net Download Page</ulink>.  Untar it using <command>tar</command>
     or WinZip on your computer.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Using your FTP client, upload the new Gallery files over the old Gallery files.
     Yes, this will override the old Gallery files, but this is OK!
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Re-run the <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">configuration
     wizard</link>.  Afterward, put Gallery back into secure mode, as described
     in that guide.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Some upgrades include changes to the Gallery data formats and
     require you to upgrade all of your albums.  You can either let
     this happen automatically the first time somebody views the
     album, or you can upgrade the albums yourself when logged in as
     an admin.  If you want to upgrade them all, open 
     <blockquote>
      <para>
       http://www.example.com/gallery/upgrade_album.php
      </para>
     </blockquote>
     in your web browser (use the real url to your Gallery, of course)
     and then follow the instructions you find there.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Enjoy your upgraded Gallery!
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  
  <note>
   <para>
    If after you upgrade your Gallery, you get a blank screen or a PHP error
    (e.g. "function not found", etc...), don't panic.  Your FTP client probably
    didn't override all the files.  The solution is to delete all the Gallery
    files except &config.php; and your albums directory and re-upload Gallery
    (don't forget to re-run the configuration wizard).
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect2>
 
 <sect2 id="gallery1-install.upgrade.modified">
  <title>Upgrading a modified Gallery</title>
  
  <para>
   Upgrading a Gallery installation you have modified can be difficult.  By modified,
   we mean modifying the actual PHP code Gallery runs on.  If you just made changes
   in the <filename>html_wrap/</filename> or <filename>css/</filename> directories, 
   you should have no worries (you should have removed the .default extension from
   the files before modifying them, so that they won't get overridden when upgrading) and
   can proceed upgrading Gallery using one of the guides above.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you indeed have modified some of the PHP code that Gallery uses, upgrading will
   be more difficult, but not totally impossible.  It will be, however, extremely hard
   or impossible to upgrade a modified Gallery without shell access to the server.  Keep
   this in mind.  First, you'll need to download the original non-modified Gallery version
   that corresponds to the version you are currently using (i.e. if you modified Gallery 1.3.4,
   re-download an unmodified Gallery 1.3.4).  Unpack it in the same directory that your modified
   Gallery is in, but name is something like <filename>orig_gallery/</filename>.  You should now
   have two directories, <filename>gallery/</filename> (or whatever your modified Gallery's directory
   name is) and <filename>orig_gallery/</filename>.  Next, run this command:
   <screen>
    diff -r -C 3 orig_gallery gallery &gt; changes.txt
   </screen>
  </para>
  <para>
   You now have a patch file containing the changes you made.  Next, download the newest version
   of Gallery (the one you want to upgrade to).  "cd" to the parent directory of the new unpacked
   Gallery.  Run this command:
   <screen>
    patch &lt; changes.txt
   </screen>
  </para>
  <warning>
   <para>
    The odds are that this won't completely work, because we may have made changes to the same
    line you changed, causing <command>patch</command> to get confused.  However, it's worth
    a try.
   </para>
  </warning>
 </sect2>
      
</sect1>
