<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery1-install.windows-iis">
 <title>Installing on a Windows Server (IIS)</title>
 
 &gallery1.upgrade;
 
 <note>
  <simpara>
   IIS is not officially supported by the Gallery Team.  These instructions are
   provided as a guide to help you with setting up Gallery on IIS, but because
   of major problems with PHP and IIS integration, IIS is not considered a
   supported platform.
  </simpara>
 </note>
 <para>
  These instructions are a slightly modified and expanded version of the steps
  previously found in the Wiki web, gathered from various forum users'
  experiences.
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Install PHP by running the installer program found at
    <ulink url="http://www.php.net/downloads.php">the PHP downloads page</ulink>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Find the &php.ini; file (should be in your system root directory, e.g.
    <filename>C:\winnt\</filename> or <filename>C:\windows</filename>.  Open
    it in Notepad.  Locate the line that starts with <literal>error_reporting
    </literal>.  Change the line to read: <literal>error_reporting = 2039
    </literal>.  Then change the line that starts with
    <literal>session.bug_compat_warn</literal> to <literal>session.bug_compat_warn = 
    0</literal>.  Next, find the line that starts with <literal>magic_quotes_gpc</literal>
    and change it to read <literal>magic_quotes_gpc = 0</literal>.  Finally,
    find the line that starts with <literal>session.save_path</literal> and make
    sure it points to a valid directory, such as <literal>C:\winnt\temp</literal>
    or <literal>C:\windows\temp</literal>.  Also find the line that starts with
    <literal>upload_tmp_dir</literal>.  Set this directive to the same thing
    as <literal>session.save_path</literal>.  <emphasis>Remember what you
    specified for these directives for a later step</emphasis>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Open the IIS panel (Start -&gt; Control Panel -&gt; Administrative Tools
    -&gt; Internet Information Services).  Right click on the "Default Website"
    (or the name of the website you're installing Gallery under) and choose
    "Properties".  Click the "Documents" tab, and click "Add".  Enter "index.php"
    and click OK.  Click OK and close the IIS panel.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Make sure the <literal>IUSR_[machinename]</literal> account has full read/write
    access to your PHP session data and upload temp directories (see step 2).
    Find the directory you specified in Windows Explorer and right click on it,
    choosing "Properties" then "Security".  If you see the <literal>IUSR_[machinename]</literal>
    account listed, make sure it has full read/write permissions.  If not, you will
    have to add this account.  Click "Add..." then "Advanced" then "Find Now".  It
    will show a list of all the user accounts available on the machine.  Find the
    <literal>IUSR_[machinename]</literal> account and click "OK" and "OK" again.  Then
    make sure the account has the proper permissions, as listed above.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Download <ulink url="http://www.imagemagick.org">ImageMagick</ulink> and
    run the installation program.  <emphasis>Do NOT install it to the default
    directory</emphasis>.  Instead, choose something like <filename>C:\ImageMagick</filename>
    or another directory <emphasis>without a space</emphasis>.  Remember this
    directory.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    If you are using <link linkend="gallery1-install.required-programs.jhead">jhead</link>
    or other optional programs, install them <emphasis>in a directory without
    a space</emphasis>.  Remember which directory you installed them in.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <ulink url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=phpWiki&amp;file=index&amp;pagename=Download">
    Download Gallery</ulink> and unpack it under your wwwroot directory.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Create two directories called <filename>albums</filename> and <filename>tmp
    </filename> in the newly created directory where you unpacked Gallery.  Give
    the <literal>IUSR_[machinename]</literal> user full read/write access to
    these two directories.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Put Gallery into config mode by running <filename>configure.bat</filename>
    in the root Gallery directory
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Run the <link linkend="gallery1-install.config-wizard">configuration wizard
    </link>.  Input all necessary information, including where you put all the
    programs you installed earlier and where you created your albums and temp
    directories (see previous step).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Complete the config wizard and run <filename>secure.bat</filename>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Search for <filename>cmd.exe</filename> on your system.  It should be in
    the <filename>C:\windows\system32</filename> or <filename>C:\winnt\system32</filename>
    folder.  Make sure the <literal>IUSR_[machinename]</literal> account has read
    and execute permissions to it. Another possible solution may be to copy cmd.exe 
    for your <filename>c:\windows\system32\</filename> folder to the same folder 
    <filename>php.exe</filename> resides in. The problem might not just be permissions, 
    but the ability to run <filename>cmd.exe</filename> from it's default location via IIS. 

   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Your Gallery should be successfully installed.  Enjoy!
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <note>
  <para>
   If you are using NetPBM, instead of ImageMagick (not recommended), you may
   need to refer to <link linkend="gallery1-install.faq.c.26">FAQ C.26</link>.
  </para>
 </note>
</sect1>
   
     
