<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery2-devguide.concepts">
 <title>Concepts</title>
 
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Test Driven Development
  </title>
  <para>
   Writing a application that must run on many different
   platforms, works with multiple databases and is based on
   emerging technologies can be very challenging. Especially when
   the development is distributed and has been in progress over a
   long period of time. As we've worked on Gallery2 we've found
   issues with the design and implementation that make us want to
   rework large parts of the system. However, we fear making
   large changes because even though G2 is modular and well
   written there are still interdependencies between different
   parts of the system and there's the chance that we're breaking
   something critical. After all, how do we have to know that our
   change is going to work on all of our platforms and databases
   without doing a lot of exhaustive and manual testing? This can
   be daunting and it tends to impose a conservative mindset
   where we fear to enact change because we know that we won't be
   able to find out the consequences until its too late. That is
   unacceptable; we must be willing to make large changes or
   we'll get stuck with an inferior design.
  </para>
  <para>
   Enter Test Driven Development.
  </para>
  <para>
   This is a strategy whereby every new bit of functionality
   starts its life as a test. We envision the feature and then
   write a test that will only succeed when the feature is
   complete. Initially when we run the test it fails because we
   haven't written the feature yet. Then we go and write the
   feature until it satisfies the test. If we think of a new
   twist or restrictrion on the feature then we write a new test
   and then keep working on the code until that test passes
   also. Pretty soon we have a very large set of tests, and all
   of our code is getting tested regularly. If we find something
   that doesn't look right, or can be combined with other code we
   can feel free to make as many small or large changes as we
   want, as long as when we check the changes in the tests still
   run. Find a bug? Write a test that fails until the bug is
   fixed. Want to add a feature? Write a test first. Code running
   slow? Refactor and optimize at will as long as the tests still
   run. Want to know if your code is going to work on a different
   platform? Go to that platform and run the tests. Find a bug on
   that platform? Write a test to expose the bug, fix the bug so
   that the test works, check it all in and then go and run the
   tests on the first platform.
  </para>
  <para>
   G2 uses a system called phpunit to do unit testing and at the time
   of this writing has about 600 tests covering almost all of the core
   feature set.  If you want to see what the test suite looks like,
   install G2 and browse to gallery2/setup/phpunit/index.php.  All the
   tests should be green, at all times.
  </para>
  <para>
   Test Driven Development is not our idea. It stems from a
   methodology called Extreme Programming. Bharat learned about
   Extreme Programming while doing development on SourceForge,
   grew enamored of it and decided that while not all principles
   could be applied to an open source project like Gallery, at
   least some of them were of tremendous value. For more
   information about Extreme Programming read these links:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.google.com/search?q=extreme+programming">
       <citetitle>
        Extreme Programming Google Links
       </citetitle>
      </ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://junit.sourceforge.net/doc/testinfected/testing.htm">
       <citetitle>
        Test Infected
       </citetitle>
      </ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.artima.com/intv/testdriven4.html">
       <citetitle>
        Test Driven Development
       </citetitle>
      </ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.xprogramming.com/xpmag/whatisxp.htm">
       <citetitle>
        What is Extreme Programming?
       </citetitle>
      </ulink>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Embedding Gallery in Other Applications
  </title>
  <para>
   Gallery is designed very specifically to manage your
   multimedia online.  It's not a content management system or a
   blog or a website editor.  However, there's no reason why
   Gallery can't be the multimedia management portion of a much
   larger system which does much more context content management
   or blogging, etc.  Many such systems focus on their core
   competency and provide a very weak multimedia management
   system.  Gallery is designed to work within those larger
   systems and provide the functionality that they lack.
  </para>
  <para>
   In order to make this process of embedding easier, Gallery is
   very careful about not polluting global namespaces.  Core
   classes, constants, database tables, etc are prefixed with
   different forms of "gallery" to identify them as separate from
   the outer program.
  </para>
  <para>
   How we actually go about embedding Gallery into another
   program depends heavily on which program we are going to work
   with.  For PHP CMS systems like PostNuke/PHP-Nuke, we will
   need to create a new entry point into G2 that replaces
   main.php. This new entry point will be PostNuke/PHP-Nuke
   specific and will give us a way to interoperate between the
   two.  Then we need to extend the database storage layer so
   that it understands that the user/group information is now
   stored in a different table/column arrangement so that our
   queries continue to function. Then we need disable certain
   functionality (like user management) and provide some new
   templates for the administration console so that we can tie
   the G2 site admin interface into the CMS' admin system.
  </para>
  <para>
   I'm envisioning shipping a snap-on pack for each CMS that
   converts your G2 install into one that works for the specific
   CMS. It'll work by adding new files/modules to the G2 install
   (but not replacing existing files).  This is in the
   speculative stage so no substantive work has been done on it
   yet.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Coding standards
  </title>
  <para>
   Clean code is important, especially when many developers are
   collaborating.  Read and obey the Gallery 2
   <ulink url="http://gallery.menalto.com/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=GalleryOldDocs&amp;file=index&amp;req=viewarticle&amp;artid=19">
    Coding Standards
   </ulink>
   document
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
