<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?> 
<!-- $Id$ -->

<sect1 id="gallery2-devguide.patterns">
 <title>Patterns</title>
 
 <para>
  Gallery makes use of quite a few design patterns in the code.
  These patterns are design and coding methodologies that make it
  easier to implement and understand large systems.  If you're
  working on the official Gallery codebase, you must understand and
  use them in the code that you write.  If you're developing your own
  module, we strongly recommend that you follow these patterns since
  it'll make it that much easier to integrate your module into the
  official module set (which is a good thing).
 </para>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Code Generation
  </title>
  <para>
   Gallery makes extensive use of code generation to save us time and
   effort in creating and maintaining source code.  We embed special
   tags into our entity and map classes which can be describe these
   classes in such a way that we can extract this information and get
   a very clear idea of what is in them.  This information is then
   used to:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Create getters and setters for all of our entity members
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Create convenience methods for maps to add, remove and update map
      entries.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Create database specific SQL scripts (right now only MySQL and
      Postgres, but we can add others).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Generate UML diagrams (only partially supported at the moment)
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   The way this works is that we embed tags in comments in the
   code that contain the string "@g2".  After these @g2 tags come bits
   of XML such that if you extract all of the @g2 tags in order from
   the file (and strip off the @g2 part) you'll get a well formed XML
   file that conforms to the lib/tools/dtd/GalleryClass2.0.dtd DTD
   specification.  
  </para>
  <para>
   For example, here's a snippet from modules/core/classes/GalleryItem.class
   <programlisting>
    /**
     * Abstract base class for all objects in the Gallery
     * composite tree
     *
     * Container for all functionality and data common objects that 
     * Gallery can deal with.  Each GalleryItem has the capacity
     * to own other GalleryItems in a parent-child relationship.
     * That capacity can be enabled or disabled by subclasses of
     * GalleryItem.
     *
     * @g2 &lt;class-name&gt;GalleryItem&lt;/class-name&gt;
     * @g2 &lt;parent-class-name&gt;GalleryFileSystemEntity&lt;/parent-class-name&gt;
     * @g2 &lt;schema&gt;
     * @g2   &lt;schema-major&gt;1&lt;/schema-major&gt;
     * @g2   &lt;schema-minor&gt;0&lt;/schema-minor&gt;
     * @g2 &lt;/schema&gt;
     * @g2 &lt;requires-id/&gt;
     *
     * @package GalleryCore
     * @subpackage Classes
     * @abstract
     */
    class GalleryItem_core extends GalleryFileSystemEntity {
    
        /**
         * Can this item contain children?
         *
         * @g2 &lt;member&gt;
         * @g2  &lt;member-name&gt;canContainChildren&lt;/member-name&gt;
         * @g2  &lt;member-type&gt;BOOLEAN&lt;/member-type&gt;
         * @g2 &lt;/member&gt;
         *
         * @var int $_canContainChildren
         * @access private
         */
        var $_canContainChildren;
   </programlisting>
   In the above snippet, if you pull out the @g2 tags you wind up with:
   <programlisting>
    &lt;class-name&gt;GalleryItem&lt;/class-name&gt;
    &lt;parent-class-name&gt;GalleryFileSystemEntity&lt;/parent-class-name&gt;
    &lt;schema&gt;
      &lt;schema-major&gt;1&lt;/schema-major&gt;
      &lt;schema-minor&gt;0&lt;/schema-minor&gt;
    &lt;/schema&gt;
    &lt;requires-id/&gt;
    &lt;member&gt;
     &lt;member-name&gt;canContainChildren&lt;/member-name&gt;
     &lt;member-type&gt;BOOLEAN&lt;/member-type&gt;
    &lt;/member&gt;
    &lt;member&gt;    
   </programlisting>
   This is only a partial listing; GalleryItem really has many more
   members than that.  However, we take this XML and wrap it in a
   &lt;class&gt; tag and it's now compliant XML.
  </para>
  <para>
   You <emphasis>never need to modify the interface classes or SQL
   files by hand</emphasis>.  You just need to keep the map and entity
   files up to date and the code generator will take care of it for
   you!  To generate the interface classes and SQL files for a module,
   just cd into the module's classes directory and run "gmake".  You
   must have the Saxon XSLT engine and an XML validator like rxp
   installed for this to work.  The saxon and rxp command lines are
   specified in lib/tools/GNUmakefile.inc, but you can override them
   on the command line:
   <programlisting>
    % cd modules/<emphasis>module-name</emphasis>/classes
    % gmake SAXON="java-jar /usr/local/share/java/classes/saxon.jar" VALIDATOR="rxp -d -s -V"
   </programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
   The interface classes are generated by combining class XML file
   with the modules/core/clases/interfaces/ClassCode.xsl XSL template.
   This is fairly straightforward.
  </para>
  <para>
   Generating the database SQL files is a little bit more complicated.
   First we convert the XML from conforming to the GalleryClass2.0 DTD
   into XML that conforms to the DatabaseTableDefinition2.0 DTD.  This
   form allows us to describe a database table in neutral terms.  If
   you want to create tables that do not draw directly from a
   GalleryMap (this is unusual and you should avoid it, but the core
   module has to do it for things like the Schema and Lock tables) you
   can create XML files that conform to the DatabaseTableDefinition2.0
   DTD and put them in
   modules/<emphasis>module-name</emphasis>/classes/GalleryStorage/DatabaseStorage/schema/xml-src.
   Next, we take these database table XML files and combine them with
   database specific XSL templates which are found in the
   .../DatabaseStorage/schema/platform directory.  Using this
   technique, we can easily guarantee that any new entity, map or
   other database table that we create will be well formed for each
   database.  It also means that we can expand to new databases
   relatively quickly since we won't have to hand-write SQL for each
   one.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Entities
  </title>
  <para>
   An entity in Gallery is an atomic chunk of data that can be loaded
   from and saved to the database and has its own internal behaviour.
   Each entity has its own unique id, creation timestamp,
   modification timestamp, serial number and entity type.  All
   entities are subclasses of GalleryEntity.  You never create an
   instance of GalleryEntity itself; it's an abstract class even
   though PHP doesn't explicitly support abstract classes.  When you
   want a new instance of an entity you should create it using the
   factory methods of GalleryCoreApi (described below).
  </para>
  <para>
   There are a variety of different types of entities that server
   different purposes.  In the Gallery object model we take advantage
   of inheritance to create subclasses of entities that contain only
   the data and behaviour that we need.  For example, groups and
   users do not have a parent/child relationship with other entities
   so they directly subclass GalleryEntity.  Everything else in the
   system has a parent/child relationship so we have a new entity
   type called GalleryChildEntity that subclasses GalleryEntity and
   contains a <emphasis>parentId</emphasis> member.  Read the UML
   diagram to see exactly how the various entities are related.
  </para>
  <para>
   Gallery data is arranged in a tree starting with a single
   GalleryAlbumItem as the root.  The root album contains other
   GalleryItems which are either GalleryAlbumItems or
   GalleryDataItems.  GalleryDataItems are the manageable data types
   such as GalleryPhotoItem or GalleryMovieItem instances.  Modules
   can introduce new item types by creating entities that extend
   GalleryDataItem and registering them with the factory methods
   of the GalleryCoreApi.
  </para>
  <para>
   GalleryEntities contain contents that have special embedded
   metadata in them.  We use this metadata to describe the entity in
   such a way that our automated tools can automatically generate
   interface classes and SQL table definitions for the entity.  This
   saves a considerable amount of time writing code by hand.  Read
   the "Code Generation" section for more details on how this works.
  </para>
  <para>
   You create a new GalleryEntity by first getting an instance of it
   from the GalleryCoreApi:
   <programlisting>
    list ($ret, $user) = GalleryCoreApi::newFactoryInstance('GalleryEntity', 'GalleryUser');
    if ($ret->isError()) { 
        return array($ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__), null); 
    }

    if (!isset($user)) {
        return array(GalleryStatus::error(ERROR_MISSING_OBJECT, __FILE__, __LINE__), null);      
    }
   </programlisting>
   Note a couple of things about the above code.  First, we know that
   we want to create a GalleryUser, and that GalleryUser extends
   GalleryEntity.  This allows us to make the specific factory call
   telling it to give us an instance of the GalleryUser class.  Now
   the nice thing is that we don't actually care what GalleryUser we
   get back as long as we get back something that fulfills the
   GalleryUser API.  This is necessary since later on when we embed
   Gallery inside another system we'll change the factory method to
   return (for example) an instance of PostNukeGalleryUser and our
   application logic will still function properly.
  </para>
  <para>
   The other thing to note is that we don't actually know for sure
   that we received back an instance of the class.  We may have asked
   for a class type that is not registered, so not only do we have to
   check for (and handle) an error code, but we have to handle the
   situation where no object was returned.  Now in the case of
   GalleryUser it's pretty unlikely that we won't have an
   implementation handy, but it's still a good pattern to check so
   that we can meet our reliability goal.
  </para>
  <para>
   It's not always going to be the case that we know exactly what
   type of entity we want, especially when we're creating new
   GalleryItem types.  Typically, we want to create a GalleryItem
   based on the mime type of the file the user just uploaded.  This
   is when the factory code really shines, since we can allow modules
   to create their own GalleryDataItem entities and register them
   with the factory so that we can simply do this:
   <programlisting>
    list ($ret, $newItem) = GalleryCoreApi::newItemByMimeType($mimeType); 
    if ($ret->isError()) { 
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }
   </programlisting>
   Note that in this example, we're going to get back a GalleryItem
   but we have no idea what the actual implementation is.  In the
   core module, we map some mime types to GalleryPhotoItem, some to
   GalleryMovieItem and the rest to GalleryUnknownItem.  But there
   may be a new module in the system that has created a
   FlashMovieItem type and registered it with the
   <emphasis>application/x-shockwave-flash</emphasis> mime type, and
   we might be getting one of those entities back if the user
   uploaded a flash movie.  We don't know, and we don't care as long
   as the entity returned is a GalleryItem.
  </para>
  <para>
   You must write lock a GalleryEntity before you modify or delete
   it.  However, you do not have to write lock it before creating the
   entity, since nothing else can modify it before you create it.
   However, you should read lock the parent to make sure that it does
   not get modified while you're creating entities inside it.Entity
   creation looks like this (without locking; see the locking section
   for examples with locking also).
   <programlisting>
    // use the factory to get a new instance of GalleryUser, as shown above
    // then call create.
    $ret = $user->create("jdoe");
    if ($ret->isError()) {
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }

    $user->setEmail("jdoe@jdoe.com");

    // Now we have a well formed instance of GalleryUser in memory so save
    // it to the database:
    $ret = $user->save();
    if ($ret->isError()) {
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }
   </programlisting>
   Modifying or deleting entities requires you to lock and refresh
   the item before you change or delete it.
   <programlisting>
    // Let's assume $user is a loaded GalleryUser entity.  First we lock it:
    list ($ret, $lockId) = GalleryCoreApi::acquireWriteLock($user->getId());
    if ($ret->isError()) {
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }

    // Then we refresh the user in case somebody modified it in the window between
    // when we loaded it and when we acquired the lock
    $ret = $user->refresh();
    if ($ret->isError()) {
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }

    // Then modify the item
    $user->setEmail("jdoe@jdoe.com");

    // Now save it:
    $ret = $user->save();
    if ($ret->isError()) {
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }

    // And then release our write lock
    list ($ret, $lockId) = GalleryCoreApi::releaseLocks($lockId);
    if ($ret->isError()) {
    return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }
   </programlisting>
   Deleting is the same as saving, except that you use the delete()
   method on the entity instead of save().  And you can also use the
   <programlisting>GalleryCoreApi::deleteEntityById()</programlisting>
   convenience method instead since that handles all the locking
   issues and doesn't require you to actually load the entity just so
   that you can delete it.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Maps
  </title>
  <para>
   Maps are a means of storing data that is not included in entities.
   All data in Gallery 2 falls within either an entity or a map.  As
   with entities, the interfaces for map classes are generated for us
   (see the Generated Code section below), but unlike entities the map
   classes do not require locking and do not inherit behaviour from a
   common base class.  In fact, maps do not inherit from other classes
   at all.  For example, in the core module, maps are used to store:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Item properties.  These are key/value pairs associated with any 
      item.  They can be used by other modules to hang any data at all
      onto an item.  We put this in a map because there is a one->many
      cardinality from items to item properties.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Module parameters.  Can store any data they want in the module
      map.  This is where modules keep track of their preferences (like
      the core module's default language settings, or the NetPBM
      module's path to the binaries).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Item attributes.  Some attributes for items (like its view counts)
      are placed in an item attribute map. The cardinality between items
      and those attributes is one to one, so you'd think that it would
      make sense to put them into the entity itself. However, you're
      required to lock an entity before changing any of them. Since these
      attributes are non-essential to the integrity of the entity itself,
      we can have them in a map to allow faster updates.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      User/Group mapping.  This is a classic tie table where we associate
      an user with a group.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   There are many other types of maps, these are just a few. Usually a 
   map class is ends with "Map", so they are easy to find. Read the
   API documentation for more specific details on each map type.
  </para>
  <para>
   Maps are pure static classes.  They should never be instantiated, but
   instead their methods should be called statically.  For example, to
   add a user to a group you'd say:
   <programlisting>
    $ret = GalleryUserGroupMap::addMapEntry($userId, $groupId);
    if ($ret->isError()) {
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }
   </programlisting>
   Usually a map will also provide a helper-class that provides common
   methods for manipulating its entries. In the above case, we have the
   following API-call:
   <programlisting>
    $ret = GalleryCoreApi::addUserToGroup($userId, $groupId);
    if ($ret->isError()) {
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }
   </programlisting>
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Helpers
  </title>
  <para>&nbsp;
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Templates
  </title>
  <para>&nbsp;
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Locking
  </title>
  <para>
   G2 employs a locking methodology called "Pessimistic
   Locking".  What this means is that whenever the application
   layer wants to change an entity that already exists in the
   system, it must lock the entity before it begins editing and
   release the lock when its done.  While this entity is
   locked, no other session can touch the entity.
  </para>
  <para>
   We use two types of locks: read locks and write locks.
   Holding a read lock on an entity means that nobody can edit
   it.  That's useful in the case where you want to make sure
   that an entity (eg, an album) doesn't get moved while you're
   working with it.  The other type of lock is a write lock.
   It allows your session the exclusive ability to edit an
   entity.
  </para>
  <para>
   The general rule is that you acquire a lock as far upstream
   as possible.  When performing complex operations (like
   moving items, etc) only the application logic really knows
   what's going on.  The framework can check to make sure that
   a lock is acquired but in general, each framework call
   doesn't know the context that it's getting called in so it
   shouldn't be responsible for acquiring the lock.
  </para>
  <para>
   For example if we're writing the the move or copy item
   logic, at the app level we want to acquire a read lock on
   the source and destination albums and on all of their
   parents.  This prevents the source/destination containers
   from getting moved around while we're moving items within
   them.  Then we want to write-lock the items we're moving so
   that nobody can fiddle with them while we're moving them.
   Thus we can successfully move or copy the items safe in the
   knowledge that our operation should complete successfully.
  </para>
  <para>
   One of the interesting problems that we address in G2 is
   avoiding data corruption.  If you're using G2 in a
   transactional database, you should never get data corruption
   in the database.  However, we don't have a journalling
   filesystem and it's common for us to do filesystem
   operations at the same time as the database operations.  If
   the database transaction fails, the database changes will be
   rolled back cleanly but we'll be left with corruption in the
   filesystem (eg, an item gets moved to a new location but
   then the database statement fails, it all rolls back but the
   file gets stranded in the new place).  In a perfect world,
   we will check our database operations and trying to undo any
   filesystem changes if it looks like the database operation
   failed.  It's not perfect (and we're not doing it properly
   in a lot of places) but it's possible.
  </para>
  <para>
   Pessimistic locking minimizes the above problem.  We assume
   that there will be concurrency issues and try to lock all
   objects that we're going to touch.  We read lock anything
   that we're not going to change and write lock anything that
   we are going to change.  The downside is that because not
   all databases have row-level locking, the locking strategy
   involves quite a few reads and writes to a lock table so
   locking is somewhat expensive.  
  </para>
  <para>
   Only GalleryEntities are locked.  Data in maps is considered
   to be of a more transient nature and less susceptible to
   concurrency issues.  So in order to minimize the expense,
   we've moved some columns out of the entities and into the map
   classes.  These columns (like view count, etc) are much
   faster because they are not protected by locks, but the
   downside is that it's possible for them to be updated
   inaccurately so they're slightly less reliable.
  </para>
  <para>
   One possible alternative to the above solution is to let the
   framework handle all locking under the covers and not expose
   it at the application logic level.  This would make new
   application logic easier to write, since you wouldn't have
   to worry about locking.  There are a few reasons why this
   won't work:
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      We don't know for sure that we have transactions, and
      we don't want to fail in the middle of an operation
      and corrupt our database and our filesystem, so we
      should try to acquire all write locks up front to
      ensure success before we make any changes.  That can
      only be done in the controller, since no other part of
      the code knows exactly what we need.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Locking is expensive in environments without good
      row-level locking (eg, MySQL) so it's best to try to
      acquire lots of locks at once instead of doing them as
      we find out that we need them.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Right after you get the write lock for an entity, you
      must refresh the entity, otherwise you don't know for
      sure that you have the latest version (somebody else
      might have had the write lock, modified the entity and
      released the lock in between the time that you loaded
      the entity and when you successfully acquire the write
      lock).  This can also only be done safely at the top.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   The framework helps out by not allowing you to save an
   entity unless it is write locked.  So the main issue is
   knowing when to acquire read locks (more on that below).
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Factories
  </title>
  <para>&nbsp;
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Model-View-Controller
  </title>
  <para>
   The Model-View-Controller (MVC) pattern is a way of organizing the code a
   program's graphical user interface (GUI).  The basic premise is to separate
   data from logic and display.
  </para>
  <para>
   <ulink url="http://ootips.org/mvc-pattern.html">
    <citetitle>
     http://ootips.org/mvc-pattern.html
    </citetitle>
   </ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
   <ulink url="http://www.phppatterns.com/index.php/article/articleprint/11/-1/1/">
    <citetitle>
     http://www.phppatterns.com/index.php/article/articleprint/11/-1/1/
    </citetitle>
   </ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
   The "Model" is the information in the database (think of "data model") it's got
   no logic.  it's just data.  The model is wrapped with logic in the core that
   allows you to manipulate it safely without screwing things up.  These are the
   entities/maps/utility classes, etc.
  </para>
  <para>
   Anything you see in your browser is a View, which is just one way of looking at
   any given model.  So you may have a GalleryUser entity as your data model. You
   can have lots of different views of that user information, one might show the
   email address, another might show a form where you can edit data.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you are looking at a View that contains an HTML form, when you submit the
   form it goes to a Controller. The Controller reads the form data and then
   applies it to the model, then redirects you to the appropriate next View
   which pulls data from the model and then shows it to you.
  </para>
  <para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The model is the data and a set of functions that accept changes to the data
      and supply the data to views.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The controller selects views and processes user input to supply to the model.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The views are methods for displaying the data supplied by the model.  They can
      also provide the visible interface to add and change data.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
   We don't do view notification (which is a component of MVC) because we don't
   actually have persistent views.  If G2 were a desktop UI application you
   could have a persistent view which would need notification. Instead, upon
   completion of a change to a model's data, a G2 controller will select a
   different view, which asks the model for the data. The controller can
   delegate to any view that it wants. We follow a pattern whereby if the
   controller receives an error, it delegates back to the view that generated
   the form.  If the controller completes successfully, it delegates (using
   redirection) to a different "success" view.
   See: Redirect-On-Post
  </para>
  <para>
   Let's take the case of editing an item as an example.
  </para>
  <para>
   The item itself is represented by a modules/core/classes/GalleryItem class.
   All that we care about is that the item is a GalleryItem, even though we know
   that it's almost definitely a GalleryPhotoItem or GalleryMovieItem, each of
   which extend GalleryDataItem which extends GalleryItem.
  </para>
  <para>
   The view (ItemEditItemView in modules/core/ItemEditItem.inc) doesn't care
   which specific kind of item the model is because it knows that it can safely
   treat the model as a GalleryItem (this is called polymorphism/abstraction).  The
   ItemEditItemView uses the modules/core/templates/ItemEditItem.tpl template
   to create an HTML form that it shows to the user.
  </para>
  <para>
   The HTML form's submit button submits the data back to the ItemEditItemController
   (also found in modules/core/ItemEditItem.inc) which loads the GalleryItem
   model back into memory and makes any necessary changes to it.
  </para>
  <para>
   The ItemEditItemController can then pass control back to the ItemEditItemView,
   or it could pass control to any other view at that point.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Internationalization and Localization
  </title>
  <para>
   We are striving to ensure that Gallery 2 runs equally well, no matter what the
   language.  Gallery 2 has an international and multilingual team of developers.
   We hope to carry our international userbase with us into the new version and
   offer them a Gallery that speaks to them in their own language wherever possible.
  </para>
  <para>
   What is UTF-8?
  </para>
  <para>
   Okay, let's start with the most bsic character set, ASCII, which has values
   0-255, representing control characters and the letters of the American
   English alphabet (and some other stuff). Obviously, in all the world's
   languages together there are more than 256 possible characters.
  </para>
  <para>
   But let's take Greek for example - it has characters like Alpha and Omega
   which can't be displayed using a single ASCII character So, someone came up
   with a 16 bit character set for greek. However, every operating system (that
   I know of) processes text using only eight-bit characters. If you want to
   represent a 16-bit character in an eight-bit world, you would use two
   eight-bit characters. Software is written for a particular character set,
   and knows how to process those character pairs into 16 bit characters and
   display the correct letter, whether it is alpha, omega, or aleph.
  </para>
  <para>
   There are three at least three different greek character encodings - three
   different ways to pair up special characters.  Software that supports Greek
   should know all three, right? This is a nightmare.
  </para>
  <para>
   Enter unicode. An international community got together and decided to define
   a huge character set that encompasses every possible character, including
   Greek, Chinese, and everything else.
  </para>
  <para>
   <ulink url="http://www.unicode.org/standard/WhatIsUnicode.html">
    <citetitle>
     http://www.unicode.org/standard/WhatIsUnicode.html
    </citetitle>
   </ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
   Unicode has a character set including thousands of characters, which is
   terrific, but faces the same problem as Greek did - existing software
   doesn't know how to deal with characters with more than 8 bits.
   several ways of encoding these big characters into 8 bits were devised,
   including UTF-2 and UTF-4 (for how many bytes were used to encode a
   character), but the one that seems to have the strongest support is UTF-8.
  </para>
  <para>
   <ulink url="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/unicode.html">
    <citetitle>
     http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/unicode.html
    </citetitle>
   </ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
   UTF-8 uses various tricks to be friendly to existing software so that
   software won't know (or care) what character set it is processing
   as long as the end-user's display understands UTF-8, life is good
   Why is gallery 2 using UTF-8? It solves the essential problem of a
   multi-language site - multiple languages on one page. If you leave a comment
   in Spanish on a Japanese site - will that site know how to display the
   diacritical marks in your words - or your name?
  </para>
  <para>
   What's the practical difference between iso-whatever and UTF-8?
  </para>
  <para>
   ISO-8859-* is a set of slightly different, language specific character sets.
   Most browsers should understand them, but you end up having trouble when you
   try to convert from one to another, or display more than one language on a
   page.
  </para>
  <para>
   That's why I suggested that we ask translators to do UTF-8. It's very
   standard and usually well supported. Other character sets may require
   specific options to be compiled into php, which isn't fun.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Storage
  </title>
  <para>&nbsp;
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Platform
  </title>
  <para>&nbsp;
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Cross-Module Interfaces
  </title>
  <para>&nbsp;
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Event Listeners
  </title>
  <para>&nbsp;
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Data Caching
  </title>
  <para>&nbsp;
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Graphics Toolkit
  </title>
  <para>&nbsp;
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Redirect-On-Post
  </title>
  <para>
   One aggravating thing about may dynamic websites is the
   situation where you want to reload a page, but the page was
   created by a form submission and reloading the page will
   submit the form again which may do something you did not
   intend.  To avoid this problem, G2 will always redirect you to
   a new page after you successfully complete an operation.  If
   you do a form post and it *doesn't* do anything (ie, it gives
   you an error) it won't redirect since it's safe to reload that
   page again if you choose.  Of course, reloading that page will
   just give you the same error, but at least it won't cause any
   damage.
  </para>
 </sect2>
 <sect2>
  <title>
   Check all return codes
  </title>
  <para>
   Reliability is one of Gallery's fundamental goals.  The path
   to reliability is to religiously check every single return
   code and make sure that when something goes wrong we handle it
   in the most appropriate way.
  </para>
  <para>
   Sadly, PHP4 lacks exception handling which means that we have
   to comeup with our own way to check return values.  G2 has its
   own system for returning status values such that errors bubble
   up to the top and can be handled at every step of the way.  We
   build up a stack trace while handling these errors and this
   stack trace can be used to diagnose problems when they occur.
  </para>
  <para>
   Any method that can fail should return an instance of a
   GalleryStatus object.  In the case of a successful result, it
   should return:
   <programlisting>
    return GalleryStatus::success();
   </programlisting>
   Upon failure, it should return the appropriate error code along
   with the relevant file name and line number like this:
   <programlisting>
    return GalleryStatus::error(ERROR_MISSING_OBJECT, __FILE__, __LINE__);
   </programlisting>
   The complete list of error codes can be found in the
   modules/core/GalleryStatus class.  The code that calls a method that
   returns a GalleryStatus object should check the error code and handle
   it properly:
   <programlisting>
    $ret = methodThatReturnsStatus();
    if ($ret->isError()) {
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }
   </programlisting>
   Note that we tag on the file and line numbers when we return the
   status code.  This is how we build up the stack trace.  We follow
   the convention that all status codes are called
   <emphasis>$ret</emphasis>.  This is a good idea in case we wish to
   refactor this code later on; it'll make those lines easier to
   find.  Note also that if your method returns other values, it
   should return an array so that the first element can be a status
   code, like:
   <programlisting>
    function foo() {
        ...
        return array(GalleryStatus::success(), "actual results");
    }
   </programlisting>
   The code calling this method should then split the return value
   in an array and first handle the status object before continuing:
   <programlisting>
    list ($ret, $results) = foo();
    if ($ret->isError()) {
        return $ret->wrap(__FILE__, __LINE__);
    }
    // Now do something with the $results here
   </programlisting>
  </para>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
